<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Falling uphill</title><description>Personal thoughts on hills, aikido, and falling</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/</link><image><url>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/favicon.png</url><title>Falling uphill</title><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/</link></image><generator>Ghost 2.9</generator><lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2019 09:42:06 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title>In pursuit of magic</title><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;Any sufficiently advanced technology is indistinguishable from magic. ~ &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clarke%27s_three_laws"&gt;Arthur C. Clarke&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I would like to offer an aikido variation of Clarke's Third Law: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;any sufficiently subtle movement is indistinguishable from magic.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id="whatwethinkmatters"&gt;What we think matters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wondered why the &lt;em&gt;up&lt;/em&gt; in press-ups and push-ups? Well, it's obvious, isn't&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/of-magic-and-other-technologies/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5c33663d2ac40f04a4902f15</guid><category>Aikido</category><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 11:28:23 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2019/01/Quotefancy-6057232-3840x2160.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;blockquote&gt;Any sufficiently advanced technology is indistinguishable from magic. ~ &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clarke%27s_three_laws"&gt;Arthur C. Clarke&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2019/01/Quotefancy-6057232-3840x2160.jpg" alt="In pursuit of magic"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I would like to offer an aikido variation of Clarke's Third Law: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;any sufficiently subtle movement is indistinguishable from magic.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id="whatwethinkmatters"&gt;What we think matters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wondered why the &lt;em&gt;up&lt;/em&gt; in press-ups and push-ups? Well, it's obvious, isn't it – we are moving our body upwards. Even so, the actual process involves pushing our hands &lt;em&gt;down&lt;/em&gt;, pushing the floor away from us. The extension through the arm moves our body upwards before the floor gives in, and hey presto!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If it's convenient, try this: get down into the bottom position of the press-up, and intend to push your body up. Go for it. Notice any tension that creeps in, and how much effort is involved. Now relax. Shake it off, if necessary. This time, intend to push the floor away from you, to push it further down into the ground, push your hands down. How much effort was involved there?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If your experience is anything like mine (it took a few goes before I could actually clearly think downwards) the actual exertion is much less than when doing a press-&lt;em&gt;up&lt;/em&gt;. It appears that&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;the body structures differently to lift the body up compared with pushing the floor down. Pushing the floor away seems to encourage a more relaxed body than trying to lift oneself up (also worth exploring with squats).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id="amipushingorareyoufalling"&gt;Am I pushing, or are you falling?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can apply the same experiment to pushing a partner, from the side with a hand on their shoulder. Are we doing a push-&lt;em&gt;up &lt;/em&gt;and tightening ourselves to push them away, or are we doing a push-&lt;em&gt;down&lt;/em&gt; and just moving them away by extending our arm?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A clear intention matters because when I extend my mind to initialise the push, it creates the feeling that the push never occurred, but that the partner just fell away* and I followed. It seems that (a) my partner responds to the intention, and (b) my muscles don't trigger in an obvious way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="smaller"&gt;[* I should add that, in this exercise, the partner is just standing without resistance. Of course, if I push him, he will move. What I'm interested in, here, is that he starts moving when I intend to push him – in other words, extending my mind starts him moving before I get the physical push going]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I receive no physical feedback that I did it, and my partner receives no physical feedback that I did it, or that he did it by volunteering to fall away, then what are we left with?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Magic!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id="youlllikeit"&gt;You'll like it,&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there we have it, &lt;em&gt;any sufficiently subtle movement is indistinguishable from magic&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id="butnotalot"&gt;but not a lot.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another reason for calling it magic is that we can't necessarily re-create it directly – it seems really soft, but when I just try to be soft, nothing happens. All I can do is attempt to re-create the container within which the magic arises. That container is created by controlling myself – lightening my posture, relaxing, being centred and expansive – and connecting with my partner.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id="andnowthetheory"&gt;And now, the theory&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, there are cells in the brain that map the body. They respond when the part of the body that they represent is touched, or when the eyes see something in close proximity to that part. Thus there is a bubble of near-space enclosing that body part – its peripersonal space. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Japan, in the late 90s, Dr. Atsushi Iriki wondered what happens to the brain's mapping of that peripersonal space when we are using tools. He taught monkeys to use rakes, wired their brains up in order to see the mind's map of the body, and sat back to see what happened.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was discovered the physical area that the cells mapped no longer extended just to the monkey's fingertips, but to the tip of the rake:– the monkey's brain was incorporating the tool into the animal's body schema. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"&gt;&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2019/01/monkey-rake-1.png" class="kg-image" alt="In pursuit of magic"&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;(a) Before learning to use a rake (left) or while passively holding the rake (right) without the intention of using it as a tool, the monkey’s hand-centered visual-tactile receptive fields stay confined to the hand’s immediate vicinity. But while the monkey is actively wielding the rake (center), the cells’ visual receptive fields expand along its length.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not just for monkeys, this ability to expand the mind's map of the body to include inanimate objects explains how we can reverse-park our car (hopefully with a fair degree of accuracy and skill), how we can hit tennis balls with a racquet, and work with any number of other tools.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In other words, "becoming one with" your tool is not a woo-woo mystical adage; it has a solid experiential and neuro-scientific underpinning.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"&gt;&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2019/01/monkey-rake-2.png" class="kg-image" alt="In pursuit of magic"&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;(b) The visual-tactile receptive field expansion of one of the monkey’s shoulder-centered neurons.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;In aikido, we want to replicate the magic or enhance it, and using partners and weapons can help with that. Just as the monkey had a rake, we have wooden training tools that serve to increase our reach. They, similarly, require moving with sensitivity and precision, and that requires purpose.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note that it is entirely possible to hold the bokken as a foreign object (see the third diagram in the first image) – which does not alter our mind mapping. What makes the difference is intention/purpose. In ki-aikido, we think along the length of the bokken, as if filling it with our spirit. Yes, that does sound strange, mystical, woo-woo, but now we're starting to see that it has a real purpose, a real effect. By unifying myself with the bokken, my brain is integrating the bokken into my body, allowing me to use it with greater precision and efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By working with weapons, we are encouraging our brain to expand its mapping of space around the body as peripersonal space. But that work has to be meaningful; we can't just wave the jo around randomly or to draw pretty arcs, we must know where we are deflecting, where we are striking at any point. That level of clarity makes the work real, which makes the jo part of us.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id="when-push-comes-to-shove-"&gt;When push comes to shove ...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Back to the push: if I extend my mind in order to push my partner, perhaps my mind is incorporating my partner into my body schema as if they were part of my body. Thus there is no sense of pushing away a separate other, just extending oneself outwards.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id="comestomove"&gt;... comes to move&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what about my partner's experience of not being pushed by me so much as just being moved? &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Being pushed and being moved do not have the same sensations. The sensation of movement is just that: movement. Someone can move us in plenty of ways: pushing, pulling, smiling, shouting, cajoling, inviting, brushing, and so on. Within all those there is information about the movement (sudden, effortless, etc) and about the instigator of the movement (he shoved me, she bumped me). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When we remove information about the instigator and their approach, we are just left with movement. My theory is that if the pusher extends their brain's map to include the pushee, it affects the pushee's experience so that they don't feel the push as an external force, at which point it becomes just movement (without a distinct source).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p class="smaller"&gt;The quote in the main image points both to the ever-present risk of self-delusion – thinking I've got something when I got nuttin' – and to the risk of not daring to go beyond what &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; know. Both threaten our development; yet the line I choose to walk is right there, constantly threatening to over-balance one way or the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="smaller"&gt;If you &lt;em&gt;already know&lt;/em&gt; what aikido is, then you're welcome to laugh at my posts and move on. If you don't, then I invite you to investigate the ideas for yourself. Either you'll learn that I'm wrong (please, let me know!) or that there's more to investigate (please, let me know!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="smaller"&gt;The theory and diagrams come from &lt;em&gt;The Body Has a Mind of Its Own&lt;/em&gt; by Sandra Blakeslee and Matthew Blakeslee, published by Random House in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p class="smaller"&gt;An aside, but related. I go bouldering at our local centre, where many of the routes are sit-starts:– the starting holds are low enough that you sit on the floor to begin. When I sit and then start to climb, the initial movement is almost always effortful. When I move into the sit as if it's already part of the climb, moving upwards is easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class="smaller"&gt;I think that's the same magic on a number of levels: I am extending my mind, or not; I am already connected with the wall, or not; I am simply moving, or not.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>States of Mind</title><description>&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;zanshin&lt;/em&gt;: continuous mind, extending mind,&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;mushin&lt;/em&gt;: no mind, &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;fudoshin&lt;/em&gt;: immovable mind, &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;shoshin&lt;/em&gt;: beginner's mind&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Blimey, where to begin?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ah, yes, obviously. Beginner's mind.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id="beginnersmind"&gt;Beginner's Mind&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shoshin&lt;/strong&gt; (初心) is a word from &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zen_Buddhism"&gt;Zen Buddhism&lt;/a&gt; meaning "&lt;strong&gt;beginner's mind.&lt;/strong&gt;" It refers to having an attitude of openness, eagerness, and lack of preconceptions when&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/states-of-mind/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5c2de93c2ac40f04a4902e00</guid><category>Aikido</category><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 07 Jan 2019 13:55:33 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2019/01/felix-mittermeier-700255-unsplash.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;zanshin&lt;/em&gt;: continuous mind, extending mind,&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;mushin&lt;/em&gt;: no mind, &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;fudoshin&lt;/em&gt;: immovable mind, &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;shoshin&lt;/em&gt;: beginner's mind&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2019/01/felix-mittermeier-700255-unsplash.jpg" alt="States of Mind"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Blimey, where to begin?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ah, yes, obviously. Beginner's mind.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id="beginnersmind"&gt;Beginner's Mind&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shoshin&lt;/strong&gt; (初心) is a word from &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zen_Buddhism"&gt;Zen Buddhism&lt;/a&gt; meaning "&lt;strong&gt;beginner's mind.&lt;/strong&gt;" It refers to having an attitude of openness, eagerness, and lack of preconceptions when studying a subject, even when studying at an advanced level, just as a beginner would. &lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;The phrase is also discussed in the book &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zen_Mind,_Beginner%27s_Mind"&gt;Zen Mind, Beginner's Mind&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shunryu_Suzuki"&gt;Shunryu Suzuki&lt;/a&gt;, a Zen teacher. Suzuki outlines the framework behind shoshin, noting "in the beginner's mind there are many possibilities, in the expert's mind there are few."&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shoshin#cite_note-1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; ~ &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shoshin"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unsurpisingly, Suzuki Sensei explains more clearly and pithily than I ever could. Beginner's mind is obviously an appropriate lens for learning; and the longer one studies, the more appropriate it is.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But what are we studying? &lt;em&gt;Aikido&lt;/em&gt; is a predominantly partner-based art, where each has a clear role. The partner exercises are actually &lt;em&gt;kata&lt;/em&gt;: prescribed forms that we aim to reproduce as precisely as possible, so that the principles of being and movement implicit within them become embodied within us. One of those principles is &lt;em&gt;continuous mind&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id="continuousmind"&gt;Continuous mind&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Zanshin&lt;/em&gt; is the state of mind that we aim to possess throughout the kata. Eventually, it becomes our usual state of mind, so that it's no longer something we need to switch to. It is the state of relaxed awareness - complete awareness of one's surroundings, whilst being ready to respond without thought or notice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If one stands opposite one's partner and switches &lt;em&gt;on&lt;/em&gt;, it's already too late. If one throws a partner and then switches &lt;em&gt;off&lt;/em&gt;, we've missed the point. The idea of continuous mind is that it is always there, ready and aware. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, we don't talk about &lt;em&gt;continuing&lt;/em&gt; our mind, rather we prefer &lt;em&gt;extending&lt;/em&gt; our mind. It has the sense of outwardness and continuation, with the result of a continuing mind.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;“The right art … is purposeless, aimless! The more obstinately you try to learn how to shoot the arrow for the sake of hitting the goal, the less you will succeed …What stands in your way is that you think that what you do not do yourself does not happen,” ~ &lt;a href="https://mayooshin.com/zanshin-art-of-focus/"&gt;Kyudo (archery) Master Kenzo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;h2 id="immovablemind"&gt;Immovable mind&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fudoshin&lt;/em&gt; is a state of equanimity or unpertubability. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Although wisdom is called immovable, this does not signify any insentient thing, like wood or stone. It moves as the mind is wont to move: forward or back, to the left, to the right, in the ten directions and to the eight points; and the mind that does not stop at all is called &lt;em&gt;immovable wisdom. ~ &lt;a href="https://budobum.blogspot.com/2015/03/states-of-mind-fudoshin.html"&gt;Takuan Soho&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;When something catches our attention, our mind is stopped by it. That it can be stopped is a sign that it is moveable. A mind that cannot be stopped, therefore, is immoveable. In Takuan's writing, immovable and unmoving are different. When your mind focuses on how your partner steps or raises a hand and then starts planning, rather than taking it in as part of a larger whole, then your mind has been moved.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;ki-aikido&lt;/em&gt;, we test for immovable mind using &lt;em&gt;ki tests&lt;/em&gt;. They are light tests of our basic structure. Not "can I push you off your spot?", but "what happens to your attention when I push lightly on you?"&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This sense of testing immovable mind allows for a moving body. Immovable mind does not equal immovable body. Rather the immovability of the mind is manifested in how the body moves in response to pressure – sometimes it is appropriate for the body to move, sometimes it is not.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id="mushin"&gt;Mushin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Literally meaning &lt;em&gt;no-mind&lt;/em&gt;, this is another linguistic puzzle. However, we can say with absolute certainty that no mind and mindlessness are not of the same ilk. Phew.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;No mind is a very quiet mind, one without preconception.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Be calm and let yourself see, hear and feel the entire situation. Instead of making a plan and figuring out what to do, just be there. When people talk about “no mind” the idea is to let the conscious, chattering, clutter of thoughts go and just be there. It’s not that you have no mind, but that you let go of the mile-a-minute constant chatter of unconsidered thought that modern life encourages and makes so difficult to escape. ~ &lt;a href="https://budobum.blogspot.com/2015/02/states-of-mind-mushin.html"&gt;The Budo Bum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This &lt;em&gt;no mind&lt;/em&gt; is a layer of our mind that comes before our verbal consciousness. It is just aware, it just knows, it just acts. Actions that come from this place tend to be very precisely, very minimal, very efficient, and very effective. And tend not to be experienced as anything &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; did, as &lt;em&gt;no mind&lt;/em&gt; operates before or below the ego (I think).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these states of mind! It is easy to get caught up by them and find your own mind whirring, never mind trying to move in concert with a pushy partner at the same time. There is only one technique in aikido, and that is the technique that can be taken out into every single aspect of life: &lt;em&gt;being awake&lt;/em&gt;. Anything is is either subsidiary to that or training for that. These states of mind are aspects of &lt;em&gt;being awake&lt;/em&gt;, and that is what real aikido is drilling into us. Not being able to do cool throws, not being able to wield a sword or staff fiercely, not looking good dressed in funky clothes. &lt;em&gt;Relaxed, open, alert, responsive and peaceful&lt;/em&gt;. That's the purpose of training; and, for the most part, that's the way to get through life.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The land welcomes you</title><description>Funny, I think – you've come here on holiday, and brought all your shit with you.</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/welcome-to-my-home/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5c2a60c0f2330941bcac3a8f</guid><category>Walking</category><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2019 00:27:32 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2018/12/burn-side-steps.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2018/12/burn-side-steps.jpg" alt="The land welcomes you"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Welcome to my home ...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have a couple of self-catering chalets on our 2-acre plot, which are usually fully booked for the spring and summer. That means we meet two new sets of strangers each week.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They come, often tired at the end of a long journey, to pick up the key. Or if we're out, we pop by to say hello when we return home. Either way, there is a moment of meeting for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I smile, introduce myself, and offer my hand.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The responses to that are &lt;em&gt;varied&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not everyone has taken my hand, though most do. Many take it and they look away; others shake it over an imaginary fence. Some barely touch it; others wring the life out of it. Yet others twist their wrist so that their hand holds mine down.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Funny, I think – you've come here on holiday, and brought all your shit with you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For them, I think, the relationship is transactional and necessary ("where should we collect the keys from?"). For us, it isn't, and that's what I want to explore.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When we moved here, looking at the huge oak and chestnut trees, wandering down to the river that has scoured seams of slate for millenia, studying the moss growing over a tumble-down rock wall, even looking at the rusted ironwork along the railway, I soon realised that we did not own this. If we insisted on putting ourselves at the centre, then we had become the stewards of this space, but that was still some human-centric stretch from the real feeling of the place.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We had become part of a landscape (though even that word is misleading), just as the moss growing on the wall, just as the bugs crawling under the moss and the buzzard hovering above it. &lt;em&gt;We belonged to it&lt;/em&gt;, not the other way round.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the English language at least, we put humans and human experience first. Subject - verb - object, every time. &lt;em&gt;I live here&lt;/em&gt;. Primacy for the human, all else relegated to background.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But that's not my experience.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Frank Forencich of Exuberant Animal writes of the&lt;em&gt; Long Body&lt;/em&gt; as human body intimately connected to habitat and tribe. Well, here we have both tribe – in our nuclear family and our paying guests – and we have habitat, the larger context within which we exist.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And I don't think our guests know that. They come, they holiday, they go. We stay, we welcome new strangers, we feel the differences between the holiday-makers from week to week, both face-to-face and through the feeling of the space of our property.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From Spring to mid-Autumn, there are short-stay strangers here most of the time. We may or may not see them daily, but they're present either physically or in our awareness. It is noticeable when the last guests of the year leave, and the human-ness of this space shrinks and quietens so that we become more aware of the &lt;em&gt;natural&lt;/em&gt; nature of this space. The birds, the trees, the weather are less backgrounded once the people have gone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For myself, my eyes soften – I can see without looking – and my ears relax, allowing me to hear without needing to listen. I can receive just by being, not needing to seek anything out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Which is not to say that's what I do. Clearly, I spend a huge amount of time spinning thoughts around in my head to little effect).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In other words, it becomes clearer that my long body includes strangers only after they've gone and we're in the shorter days of the year. Then the local world becomes a bit quieter and proportionately less human. The light of day is somewhat dimmed so that the sharp outlines and contrasts of spring and summer aren't so crisp. Noises are muffled by the quietness of birds and the increased hiss of the river's flow as more rain falls. Even midday walking-the-dog takes on a gloom.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Failing to teach</title><description>&lt;p&gt;For a while, the club had a strong-wristed student who had previously studied &lt;em&gt;karate&lt;/em&gt;. His posture and movement announced very clearly his deeply-grounded stability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the last times he attended, we studied 1st form &lt;em&gt;nikkyo&lt;/em&gt;, and came unstuck. From previous experience, it's moments like these that offer most learning,&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/failing-to-teach/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5c2de96a2ac40f04a4902e06</guid><category>Nikkyo</category><category>1st form</category><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 20:45:43 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2019/01/nikyo-sepia-1000.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2019/01/nikyo-sepia-1000.jpg" alt="Failing to teach"&gt;&lt;p&gt;For a while, the club had a strong-wristed student who had previously studied &lt;em&gt;karate&lt;/em&gt;. His posture and movement announced very clearly his deeply-grounded stability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the last times he attended, we studied 1st form &lt;em&gt;nikkyo&lt;/em&gt;, and came unstuck. From previous experience, it's moments like these that offer most learning, so here's my post mortem.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The challenge with studying aikido is to remember that we are not learning techniques in the way we might follow a map (turn left here, next go straight and then turn right); rather, we are creating a context within which we can study how to be and how to move with a particular feeling.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once we see the &lt;em&gt;nikkyo&lt;/em&gt; as an exercise within which certain principles are embedded, just waiting to be revealed, we can allow ourselves to become more sensitive to what's going on. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a teacher, I have something in mind when I call a student's attention to a particular detail. &lt;em&gt;Here, look at this, isn't it interesting? How might it change things?&lt;/em&gt; But if we think that a martial art is solely about fighting or self-defence, we may have the view that I should impose my superior technical skill upon him until he has to submit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This difference of perspective is precisely why I refer to the complementary roles of &lt;em&gt;nage&lt;/em&gt; (thrower) and &lt;em&gt;uke&lt;/em&gt; (receiver of the throw) as &lt;em&gt;partners&lt;/em&gt;, not opponents or attackers or enemies. When we enter a context as opponents, victory is gained by one vanquishing the other; when we work as partners, victory is victory for both (though how that looks precisely depends upon one's role).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then, add to that, the complementary roles of teacher and student, and we have a complex relationship going on. Are we attending this exercise as opponents or partners? Are we studying together, or am I teaching you? As teacher, it's my job to work with you in order to draw you to a greater level of skill. As a partner, it's my job to work with myself to develop greater resilience through sensitivity. As an opponent, it's my job to thwart you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a teacher, all too often, I want to investigate a particular detail and set the exercise up so that we can both study it comfortably. If I wanted to study that detail in a realistic context, that detail probably wouldn't emerge. In the case of &lt;em&gt;nikkyo&lt;/em&gt;, I wanted to look at how we twist around our partner's wrist rather than press on it, but for real he should already have lost his balance so that there is no opportunity to press on the wrist as it is already falling away.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To study the detail, I allowed him to stand up balanced but then his structure allowed him to resist. "This doesn't work on me," was his response.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As I write this, it seems simple and straightforward to resolve in the moment, but then it wasn't and I couldn't quite get my head around it. Days later I realised another complication:– I wasn't showing him how I do &lt;em&gt;nikkyo&lt;/em&gt; on him, I was showing him how to do &lt;em&gt;nikkyo&lt;/em&gt; on someone else, specifically a beginner.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our 1st form &lt;em&gt;nikkyo&lt;/em&gt; has at least 5 different possibilities in a single set of movements. To be clear, I don't mean different movement variations; I mean different mind movements within the physical movement. Yeah, that doesn't help much, does it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;once the &lt;em&gt;nikkyo&lt;/em&gt; wrist relationship is in place, you can extend your mind down through your fingers draping over the wrist&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;down the front of your partner&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;down through your partner's head&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;projecting through their little finger back to their head&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;projecting your fingers down and in to your own One Point&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Each way expresses more power as a result of the mind's projection, and is experienced as more powerful by the &lt;em&gt;uke&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So why, when working with a strong-wristed, stable &lt;em&gt;karateka&lt;/em&gt; was I sticking with the first way. It wasn't enough to persuade him down, so why didn't I escalate until he succumbed?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Because I'm teaching him the ladder so that he can use it with others. If I only teach him what works on him, he will not have all the options available when dealing with others. If his next &lt;em&gt;uke&lt;/em&gt; is a weak-wristed beginner, and he only has the nuclear option, he will hurt or damage them and they won't come back for more.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This isn't simply a case of being nice to others. It's also about helping them to develop stronger wrists – give them a &lt;em&gt;nikkyo&lt;/em&gt; they can handle, and they will stay with it long enough to stretch their wrists. Give them a sharp &lt;em&gt;nikkyo&lt;/em&gt;, and they will slam down without benefit to their own suppleness or strength.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When we &lt;em&gt;uke&lt;/em&gt; for someone, we are not simply offering ourselves up as cannon-fodder, patiently being thrown around until it's our turn to do the fun stuff! In fact, &lt;em&gt;ukemi&lt;/em&gt; is frequently thought of as the place where the real learning and transformation occurs. &lt;em&gt;Ukemi is the process by which the uke is opened and unlocked&lt;/em&gt; (I want to put this in quotation marks, but can't find the citation).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We walk into a dojo stiff with preconceived ideas, stiff with nerves, stiff with movement habits. Aikido (undoubtedly all the martial arts) is a transformative practice – you do not leave as the same person plus a few techniques, you have changed, you have been unlocked physically (greater suppleness and sensitivity), mentally (greater resilience and intent), and emotionally (greater freedom from emotional constraints).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That is the process of &lt;em&gt;ukemi&lt;/em&gt;, and therefore how we do &lt;em&gt;nikkyo&lt;/em&gt; matters deeply. It is not a technique that looks uniformly one way; it is a mode of relationship to another person who is putting pressure on you. It is not a device to conquer an opponent; it is a study of subtlety.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Thresholds and Liminal Spaces</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Our dojo is a temporary space:– during the day it’s a dusty village hall; in the evenings, it becomes a sacred space of learning.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Before the dojo exists, there is only &lt;em&gt;Outside&lt;/em&gt; (a community hall, profane existence, the usual). We create the &lt;em&gt;Inside&lt;/em&gt;, the dojo, by passing over the&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/thresholds-and-liminal-spaces/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5c2d60ed1afce07a4aa7bf1a</guid><category>Aikido</category><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 01:15:55 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2019/01/Takamatsu-Castle-Building-Interior-M3488.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2019/01/Takamatsu-Castle-Building-Interior-M3488.jpg" alt="Thresholds and Liminal Spaces"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our dojo is a temporary space:– during the day it’s a dusty village hall; in the evenings, it becomes a sacred space of learning.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Before the dojo exists, there is only &lt;em&gt;Outside&lt;/em&gt; (a community hall, profane existence, the usual). We create the &lt;em&gt;Inside&lt;/em&gt;, the dojo, by passing over the threshold - through liminal space. Literally, of course, each student passes through the doorway, and many schools of martial arts require that students pause to bow in the doorway, but this liminal space is larger and longer (temporally) than the doorway itself.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our liminal space is created by a process, a series of steps that serve to bring the participants from the outside, the profane world, to the inside, the sacred moment. The steps exist as rings around our central stage, each of which demands attention and negotiation before one can move on to the next:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Entering the room&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Cleaning the room&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Laying down the mats&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Putting up the signs&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Changing our clothes&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Bowing before stepping on to the mat&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Lining up in &lt;em&gt;seiza &lt;/em&gt;(kneeling), bowing&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Warming up together&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course, any one of these exists as a mundane step that just has to be done - you can’t practise in your work clothes comfortably, so you change into something appropriate for the occasion. At the same time, it also exists as a doorway through which one can catch a glimpse of another world. Of course, the Aikido kit (&lt;em&gt;kidogi&lt;/em&gt;) is a sturdy cotton material appropriate for physical activity, pulling and pushing, &lt;em&gt;AND&lt;/em&gt; it transports us to a world of martial spirit, crisp lines, cleanliness, and death. &lt;em&gt;Kidogi&lt;/em&gt; is traditional Japanese underwear, so it’s not surprising that it’s white, much like my string vest. However, white is also the traditional Japanese colour of death, so we are also garbing ourselves in funereal attire to prepare for death.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Robert Bly’s exploration of men and masculinity, &lt;em&gt;Iron John&lt;/em&gt;, the hero of the tale sets off to war on a three-legged nag, but the wild man of the woods (Iron John himself) provides him with a four-legged, nostril-flaring and -steaming, ground-thumping steed, shining and powerful. This speaks to the transformation that we experience (usually in retrospect) during our practice - we come in, limping from a day in the office, perhaps tired, perhaps a bit overwhelmed. By the end of the class, we’ve often experienced a moment of our own brilliance (or witnessed our partner’s), and return to the outside world refreshed, re-girded, and full spirited.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By returning to this ritual space week after week, year after year, we start to bring our transformed brilliance out with us when we return to the outside world. We start to walk taller, we begin to honour and speak our truths, we withstand discomfort without collapsing or pushing it away. We begin to live from our Inside - the Inside of the dojo has created a space for and awareness of our inner warrior. We find that we have a guide within us who seeks to help us navigate through the Outside.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And the death? Every time we fall over, every time we fail, we have an opportunity to die a little on the mat. And every single small death is a shedding of an old skin, bringing a new, lithe skin to the surface. Every small death invites us to let go of the old knowledge and experience, and to open up to new possibilities. This, then, is a death to be sought out and celebrated!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Extend your mind</title><description>&lt;p&gt;A simple phrase that contains universes! The two meanings that I am working on are &lt;em&gt;intention&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;awareness&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Intention here does not mean "I'm going to ... at some point in the future". It means using the mind to create direction, e.g. if I point to you, a direction is&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/principle-4-extend-your-mind/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5c2b8c32b44f424bb6abe260</guid><category>principles</category><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 16:00:38 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2019/01/kyudo.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2019/01/kyudo.jpg" alt="Extend your mind"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A simple phrase that contains universes! The two meanings that I am working on are &lt;em&gt;intention&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;awareness&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Intention here does not mean "I'm going to ... at some point in the future". It means using the mind to create direction, e.g. if I point to you, a direction is created from me to you that travels down along my arm, hand, finger, and continues through the air to you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the same time, when we extend our mind, we increase our awareness, so that our nervous system is retrieving more information.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is both being and doing, receptive and active, awareness and intention.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regular practice has a subtle effect on the body – which for the first months of training may not show up at all – but over time contributes to a clear feeling (i.e. sensations of wholeness, of direction) through the body.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I first started training, when told to extend my mind I would think strongly in a direction, without any internal feedback from my body. Then someone would test my structure, and I'd see that I had gained stability. After a period of this, when we went to the pub at the end of the class, I was aware of a certain feeling of aliveness (beyond that of simply having been moving for 2 hours). It felt good. After a further period, I started to notice that feeling lingering when I woke up the following morning. And so the feeling became a more frequent and longer-staying guest, until it became quietly resident in my system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As to what actually happens when we extend our mind – I'm not sure, but reading &lt;em&gt;&lt;em&gt;Born To Walk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/em&gt; recently may have given me a clue. When walking, as we bring our weight on to one leg to free up the other, the fascia in that leg gets stretched, and at a certain point of stretch, the fascia sends signals to the local muscles to prompt them to contract slightly (isometrically). This combination of fascial tissue stretch and slight muscular contraction stiffens the leg, thus stabilising it to bear our weight.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Have a Light Posture</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Stand tall, allow uplift, experience the ground pushing your skeleton upwards.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/principle-3-have-a-light-posture/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5c2b8bebb44f424bb6abe25a</guid><category>principles</category><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 15:49:44 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2019/01/hudson-hintze-268381-unsplash.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2019/01/hudson-hintze-268381-unsplash.jpg" alt="Have a Light Posture"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stand tall, allow uplift, experience the ground pushing your skeleton upwards.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Completely Relax</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Do this. Lots.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/principle-2-completely-relax/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5c2b738bf2330941bcac3b0b</guid><category>principles</category><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 14:05:23 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2019/01/anna-sullivan-687933-unsplash.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2019/01/anna-sullivan-687933-unsplash.jpg" alt="Completely Relax"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Do this. Lots.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Think of your One Point</title><description>&lt;p&gt;This is frequently the very first instruction I give to a new student. They tense their abdomen, and even prod around it, until they become aware of a place where they can't find resistance. That absence of tension defines the One Point (the &lt;em&gt;seika tanden&lt;/em&gt;, also the s&lt;em&gt;eika no&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/principle-1-think-of-your-one-point/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5c2b72fcf2330941bcac3b05</guid><category>principles</category><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 14:03:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2019/01/heidi-sandstrom-120382-unsplash.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2019/01/heidi-sandstrom-120382-unsplash.jpg" alt="Think of your One Point"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is frequently the very first instruction I give to a new student. They tense their abdomen, and even prod around it, until they become aware of a place where they can't find resistance. That absence of tension defines the One Point (the &lt;em&gt;seika tanden&lt;/em&gt;, also the s&lt;em&gt;eika no itten&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But my view of it has changed enough over the years for me to think that I misunderstood the instruction when I first heard it. I was prodding down the front of my abdomen, seeking a lack of tension at or just under my skin, which I didn't quite find so I felt the One Point to be a vague, nebulous concept.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the intervening years, as I taken up sports and activities that require more core strength, I've learnt about the layers of muscles and tissues that create lines of tension/strength/power in different directions &lt;em&gt;around&lt;/em&gt; the abdomen. And, of course, deep inside those layers there are cavities full of organs. By definition, these areas cannot tense up; they can only be squeezed by the muscles around them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, now I look for my One Point in the middle of a hollow core of strength created by multiple lines of muscles and tissues pulling in opposing and complementary directions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My best analogy so far is two-fold. Perhaps, as a child, you had pencil, paper, and ruler. Perhaps you drew a straight line, and then another just overlapping it but in a slightly different direction. And another, and another, until all these straight lines combined to sketch the outline of a rough circle.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The circle exists only as the result of multiple lines pulling in different directions. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now, let's give the analogy a third dimension – consider a leather football. It is made up of multiple small hexagonal panels and stitching. But the ball has a definite centre. There's nothing other than air inside the ball, and yet its centre is real. Geometrically, the ball has a centre. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That centre exists and doesn't, at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Slice the ball in two, and there's nothing to be found. Put them back together, press on one side of the ball, and the opposite side will respond equally – the pressure has travelled through the centre.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So could help me make sense of the One Point? For a long time, the Chinese have referred to the &lt;em&gt;dantien,&lt;/em&gt; and the Japanese to the &lt;em&gt;tanden&lt;/em&gt;, as the sphere of power (strength, energy) in the lower abdomen. Of course, there is strength there expressed through the contraction of the multiple muscles in the area. There is also a central point of emptiness in the middle, that performs as the central point around which the &lt;em&gt;tanden&lt;/em&gt; rotates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you &lt;em&gt;Think of your One Point&lt;/em&gt;, you make that point the origin for subsequent movement, giving both power and balance to it, strength and stability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the &lt;em&gt;tanden&lt;/em&gt; is the compass; the One Point is the central point on which the two-headed compass arrow rests and rotates. Perhaps the &lt;em&gt;tanden&lt;/em&gt; is the spinning top; the One Point is the legendary point of stillness at the centre of the spinning.	&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>1st form ikkyo – on the move</title><description>&lt;p&gt;1st form ikkyo – on the move.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;uke&lt;/strong&gt;: the partner that offers the attack&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;nage&lt;/strong&gt;: the partner that responds&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The basic exercise starts with the wrist hold, and the uke waits patiently for the nage to start their movement. (The uke is waiting like the water behind a dam: as soon&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/1st-form-ikkyo-on-the-move/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5c2a05e38534ab3ac3db866e</guid><category>Class Notes</category><category>Aikido</category><category>1st form</category><category>Ikkyo</category><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 12:04:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2019/01/photo-1546104962-a4f847c389e4.jpeg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2019/01/photo-1546104962-a4f847c389e4.jpeg" alt="1st form ikkyo – on the move"&gt;&lt;p&gt;1st form ikkyo – on the move.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;uke&lt;/strong&gt;: the partner that offers the attack&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;nage&lt;/strong&gt;: the partner that responds&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The basic exercise starts with the wrist hold, and the uke waits patiently for the nage to start their movement. (The uke is waiting like the water behind a dam: as soon as the dam moves, so does the water, without opinion).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It gives the nage time to work out what they need to do – good for the earliest stages of study.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the move, the uke starts and continues forward all the way through. The nage has a certain confidence in their movement, so is starting to study the importance of timing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this version of ikkyo, we take a step back to the corner. Done too early, and the uke will just re-direct their push to move with us. Done too late, and the uke's push will already be on top of us. Done just right, and the uke has committed straight forward to find that we're out of the way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So we looked at what constitutes good timing. We want to drop the uke down as they grasp us, but they have already built speed up by the time of contact. Therefore, dropping them as they meet us is too late, and we can feel their force bumping us backwards.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Right at the start of the uke's movement (before it's visible), their centre of gravity moves forward within their body. Soon after that, it is in front of their body going forwards, and their body is committed to following it, creating the forward momentum.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At that initial moment, their movement is smallest and slowest, and therefore most easy to influence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If we think strongly and clearly down then and there, it can draw their centre of gravity down rather than forwards, and their body will follow it downwards (this may be obvious from the outside or not). If we have disrupted their movement in that way, their body will be travelling downwards as well as forwards when they grasp our hand, which (a) lessens their horizontal momentum, and (b) makes the uke want to move upwards (the next part of the ikkyo).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So that was our experiment for much of the evening – we're influencing the uke at a distance by extending our mind out to them. How can this be?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recent neuroscientific research suggests that, in effect, we continue to exist beyond the physical boundaries of our skin. We have nerve sensors that can gain information from the space around us (and put information out into that space). This is what allows us to intuit how someone else is feeling - because our nervous system is reading their system's output.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is also evidence to suggest that we influence each other &lt;em&gt;through the space between us&lt;/em&gt; - a fairly straightforward mammalian skill. Perhaps body language, perhaps something more subtle still (which really just means: less visible to humans). We are apes, which are strongly societal animals, and so are sensitive to our environment and those around us. We can receive information; we can put out information.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The interesting question is:&lt;em&gt; how we can influence others around us?&lt;/em&gt; A particularly human response might be: by talking. But we all know there's something else too - if there's anxiety in the room, we start to become anxious. If one person can remain calm amid anxiety, others can start to calm down too.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Back to aikido, if our uke moves forward, we can influence them down by dropping our intention strongly down.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Homework, if you're in the mood. Move quietly this week, listen to the space around you with more than your ears. See if you can feel others enter and leave your presence, your space beyond your skin. Quiet, open attention. Maybe start with attending to the space in front of you. Then behind; then to one side; then another.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Extra homework for those who are keen: if you go to the loo in the middle of the night, try to navigate your way without turning lights on, and without relying on holding your arms out. Just sense your way in the dark.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;#pandancakealsomakesyouhappy#mindandbodyworkingtogether #dontbethethingthatgoesbumpinthenight&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Every Thursday evening, 7.30pm, Roybridge Hall.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>13th form ikkyo</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Last night: 13th form &lt;em&gt;ikkyo&lt;/em&gt;. Well, high time that we considered some of the later ki-development exercises. Of course, as ever, there's a lot in that one!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We also made a point of starting the exercise &lt;em&gt;waaay&lt;/em&gt; before contact, so that the &lt;em&gt;uke&lt;/em&gt; could never get a sense of controlling&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/13th-form-ikkyo/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5c2a06338534ab3ac3db8671</guid><category>Class Notes</category><category>Aikido</category><category>Ikkyo</category><category>13th form</category><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 02 Nov 2018 12:06:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2019/01/james-wheeler-1149191-unsplash.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2019/01/james-wheeler-1149191-unsplash.jpg" alt="13th form ikkyo"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last night: 13th form &lt;em&gt;ikkyo&lt;/em&gt;. Well, high time that we considered some of the later ki-development exercises. Of course, as ever, there's a lot in that one!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We also made a point of starting the exercise &lt;em&gt;waaay&lt;/em&gt; before contact, so that the &lt;em&gt;uke&lt;/em&gt; could never get a sense of controlling through their grip.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finished with investigating the &lt;em&gt;ikkyo&lt;/em&gt; pin a bit more closely, including attempting a single-finger pin through the back (almost worked when &lt;em&gt;uke&lt;/em&gt; tried to press himself up, not when he rolled his spine to get up – something to work on).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If none of this makes sense when you read it, then come and see what it is that we do. We run around (occasionally); we get bogged down in detail (frequently); I talk too much (all the time); we drink tea and eat ginger cake (the perfect amount). What more could you ask for?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;#gingermakesyouhappy&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Nikkyo night!</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Nikkyo night!!!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Actually, we started with the rowing exercise as per the warm-up, but with a partner moving in response to our movement. I thought it would be mildly interesting, and very light in touch. It turned out to be really sweaty work - constantly moving a partner, and the&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/nikkyo-night/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5c2a06728534ab3ac3db8674</guid><category>Class Notes</category><category>Aikido</category><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jun 2018 11:07:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2019/01/nikyo-sepia-1000-1.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2019/01/nikyo-sepia-1000-1.jpg" alt="Nikkyo night!"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nikkyo night!!!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Actually, we started with the rowing exercise as per the warm-up, but with a partner moving in response to our movement. I thought it would be mildly interesting, and very light in touch. It turned out to be really sweaty work - constantly moving a partner, and the partner constantly moving. I'll have to remember this one for mid-winter when the heaters aren't working ...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then: 1st form nikkyo. There are so many ways to over-complicate this one, and I think we tried most of them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To start, we just looked at covering our uke's grasp on the wrist. A desire to keep hold of the uke actually makes us weaker. Rather, just sticking some glue to their hand seems to work better.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I think this is an example of immovable mind - when we try to keep hold, our mind is being disturbed by their actions and reacting. When we allow them to move and trust in the glue, our mind stays still, open, and unmoved. And they don't get away so easily.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pretty much all of nikkyo is a study of immovable mind (one that cannot be disrupted by the other person's actions): as we drop our hand over the uke's wrist, that physical contact can provoke pushing and, hey presto, it ain't working. If, instead, we extend our mind through our fingers to draw a line down the centre of uke's front, it works again. When that still doesn't work, we can attend in greater detail to uke's front, until our attention is more interesting than our uke's wrist is distracting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm not sure I have much more to say!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Willing to move</title><description>&lt;p&gt;First of all, we did some quiet breathing whilst placing attention at points around the body – One Point (in the abdomen), wrists, fingers, soles of feet, scalp. In all these places, the inhale/exhale cycle was creating quiet expansion and release (contraction is too active a word). Over time we&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/willing-to-move/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5c2a069d8534ab3ac3db8677</guid><category>Class Notes</category><category>Aikido</category><category>1st form</category><category>Kotegaeshi</category><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jun 2018 11:07:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2019/01/7-seth-1156721-unsplash.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2019/01/7-seth-1156721-unsplash.jpg" alt="Willing to move"&gt;&lt;p&gt;First of all, we did some quiet breathing whilst placing attention at points around the body – One Point (in the abdomen), wrists, fingers, soles of feet, scalp. In all these places, the inhale/exhale cycle was creating quiet expansion and release (contraction is too active a word). Over time we became aware of the whole body expanding and releasing by way of all these locations moving.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then on to a few Ki development exercises: crossing wrists at One Point, crossing wrists in front of face, swing arms around body, arms out from side (but without bending forward this time), rowing exercise, raising hands to eye level.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In all these exercises, we found a similar expansion and release occurring through the body, this time driven by our intention (&lt;em&gt;extending our mind&lt;/em&gt;) rather than our breath.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Why this quiet examination? Because one of the class twisted his back recently, and is still considerably inhibited by it. Part of noticing these subtle movements is tracing them back along their lines to the lower back. We can encourage movement in a stiffened area by moving lightly in other areas - it allows movement within the stiffness, without challenging parts that aren't ready to move.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last week, we looked at how the &lt;em&gt;nage&lt;/em&gt; moves lightly in response to a push or the intention to push. This week, we studied the &lt;em&gt;uke&lt;/em&gt;'s role a bit more.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We emphasised the holding hand as a listening device, requiring a light, responsive hold rather than a vice-like grip. As the &lt;em&gt;nage&lt;/em&gt; walked backwards, the &lt;em&gt;uke&lt;/em&gt; was encouraged to move forwards without their grip on the wrist either tightening or loosening, and without their body leaning forwards or backwards - the spine just sitting neutrally atop the pelvis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As we move, we always have unbendable arm, but it should never be obvious in this exercise - if your partner feels your unbendable arm, it means that you've continued moving after they've stopped. The whole point of this listening-driven movement is to minimise the amount of information going back to the &lt;u&gt;&lt;em&gt;nage&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/u&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally &lt;a href="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/tag/form-1/"&gt;1st form&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/tag/kotegaeshi/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;kotegaeshi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, now with both partners fully performing their role - aiming for total synchronisation of movement, rather than one person leading the other around. Someone commented that they felt nothing when doing the exercise this way, and that's the point. They are giving less information away about their movement/intention, and they are receiving less from their partner.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;#willingtomove #movelikeyourlifedependsonit&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Warming up</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Our warm-up has two parts: &lt;em&gt;ki for health&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;ki development&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the &lt;em&gt;ki for health&lt;/em&gt; exercises is to awaken, loosen, and invigorate our body – to get our blood and lymph flowing. It also starts the process of bringing body and mind (attention and intention) together. So we&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/warming-up/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5c2a06da8534ab3ac3db867a</guid><category>Class Notes</category><category>Aikido</category><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 25 May 2018 11:08:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2018/12/ken-treloar-397758-unsplash.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2018/12/ken-treloar-397758-unsplash.jpg" alt="Warming up"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our warm-up has two parts: &lt;em&gt;ki for health&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;ki development&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the &lt;em&gt;ki for health&lt;/em&gt; exercises is to awaken, loosen, and invigorate our body – to get our blood and lymph flowing. It also starts the process of bringing body and mind (attention and intention) together. So we aim to give attention to what and how we're doing the exercise and how it feels; we follow lines of intention (letting intention quicken into movement).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once our body has loosened somewhat, the blood has started flowing a bit more, and our intention is leading the movement, we're ready to start the next set of exercises.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;ki development&lt;/em&gt; exercises are drawn from moments of aikido for the most part, so what we are studying in isolation will feed back into the aikido later.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are aiming to continue releasing unnecessary tension in the body, to move with intention, and to minimise effort as we do so. So these exercises should still stretch us, they should help us relax further, and they should take place within the constant expansion created by uplifting our posture and relaxing our body.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The more we engage our intention, the less we need to engage our muscular body*, until the shapes we make are just the minimal forms required, and the innate strength therein is found by extending our minds**.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Which brings me onto last night's class. We studied &lt;em&gt;ikkyo-undo&lt;/em&gt; (raising hands to eye level) eight-ways (&lt;em&gt;happo-undo&lt;/em&gt;). We tested stability at the end of the eight count, to check that we could maintain our attention and coordination through the entire exercise; then we tested randomly to ensure that we were also present to each and every moment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then: last week someone asked if the &lt;em&gt;uke&lt;/em&gt; should be "willing to move" (I think they should), so we explored how that looks, feels, and the effect of it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We started by one partner pushing firmly through the other's back, with the other trying to stay put. Inevitably, they were pushed over, stumbled, and staggered their way back to stability. Then the priority became maintaining stability in oneself ("coordination of mind and body"), without committing to standing in that single place. It became easy to walk the momentum of the push out of the system, rather than trying to stabilise around it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then, hands on back, deciding to push, and pushing. The person being pushed started to listen for the decision and move in response to that rather than waiting for the push. The result: the pusher couldn't push - as they tried to, their partner disappeared. The next result: the pusher lost their balance, and had to recover by stepping forward.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So we took that into a whole bunch of starts of aikido exercises: each time the &lt;em&gt;uke&lt;/em&gt; initiated by pushing forwards, but the &lt;em&gt;nage&lt;/em&gt; was stepping back (or to the corner, or turning) in the moment of the push, so no traction was ever gained. It became very clear that the &lt;em&gt;uke&lt;/em&gt;'s intention to push the &lt;em&gt;nage&lt;/em&gt; is the point where their stability is compromised; and it became equally clear that &lt;em&gt;ALL&lt;/em&gt; the &lt;em&gt;nage&lt;/em&gt; has to do is listen and respond to the &lt;em&gt;uke&lt;/em&gt;'s intention.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;How can we feel the &lt;em&gt;uke&lt;/em&gt;'s intention - the mechanics of it? I don't know. But we can start by guessing - &lt;em&gt;was that it?&lt;/em&gt; - and moving. If it is wrong, it'll soon show up. If it was right, the body gains a useful experience.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;#firstnightwithouttheheatersonthisyear #donutswithtea #whiskyafterclass&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* &lt;em&gt;the less we need to engage our muscular body&lt;/em&gt;: I'm crudely splitting the body into muscles that we can directly control, and other stuff (including muscles that we can only indirectly access – through imagination). Given a fairly normal amount of internal self-awareness (&lt;em&gt;interoception&lt;/em&gt;), we can experience what certain parts of us are doing (&lt;em&gt;my belly's rumbling, my back's aching, my biceps are contracting&lt;/em&gt;), but have no experience of what's going on with other parts. For example (and I consider my self-awareness to be more highly developed than normal), I know from anatomy books that I have psoas muscles connecting my spine to my femurs, but I have no clear awareness of them or the state they're in.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Having said all that, I'm viewing my &lt;em&gt;muscular body&lt;/em&gt; as the muscles I'm aware of and that I think I have direct control of. For example, it's possible to hold my arm out in front of me horizontally, and to contract the arm muscles to keep it rigid (muscular body). It's also possible to imagine it drifting up as if on a rising tide, which allows the arm to stay soft and the arm muscles uninvolved. It's possible to walk by thrusting our legs forwards and then engaging them to pull the body forwards – which is soon tiring, and so clearly of the muscular body. It's also possible to walk in a much more relaxed way, in which the legs swing freely forwards in a way that keeps the momentum going with minimal effort. Of course muscles are contracting, but my experience is not primarily muscular, it is springy and free (poor scientific terms and subjective, I'll admit!).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* &lt;em&gt;extending our minds&lt;/em&gt;: a simple phrase that contains universes! Sometimes I think it means using intention to create direction, e.g. if I point to you, a direction is created from me to you that travels down along my arm, hand, finger, and continues through the air to you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the same time, it may also mean opening our awareness up further, so that our nervous system is retrieving more information from a greater distance. Or it may mean improving the communication between conscious mind and unconscious (the nervous impulses land here first before emerging into our conscious awareness).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In short, I think of it as both being and doing, awareness and intention.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It has a subtle effect on the body – which for the first months of training may not show up at all – but over time contributes to a clear feeling (i.e. sensations of wholeness, of direction) through the body.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I first started training, when told to extend my mind I would think strongly in a direction, without any internal feedback from my body. Then someone would test my structure, and I'd see that I had gained stability. After a period of this, when we went to the pub at the end of the class, I was aware of a certain feeling of aliveness (beyond that of simply having been moving for 2 hours). It felt good. After a further period, I started to notice that feeling lingering when I woke up the following morning. And so the feeling became a more frequent and longer-staying guest, until it became quietly resident in my system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As to what actually happens when we extend our mind – I'm not sure, but reading &lt;em&gt;Born To Walk&lt;/em&gt; recently may have given me a clue. When walking, as we bring our weight on to one leg to free up the other, the fascia in that leg gets stretched, and at a certain point of stretch, the fascia sends signals to the local muscles to prompt them to contract slightly (isometrically). This combination of fascial tissue stretch and slight muscular contraction stiffens the leg, thus stabilising it to bear our weight.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Balance</title><description>&lt;p&gt;So much this evening!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We started with standing &amp;amp; shifting our weight up over our feet, rather than standing on our toes. Several things happened: first off, folk leaning forwards over their feet, but leaving their heels behind so that their weight moved forward in their body &amp;amp; they lost&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/balance/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5c2a07048534ab3ac3db867d</guid><category>Class Notes</category><category>Aikido</category><category>5th form</category><category>Kokyunage</category><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 10 May 2018 22:09:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2019/01/christophe-hautier-774462-unsplash.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/content/images/2019/01/christophe-hautier-774462-unsplash.jpg" alt="Balance"&gt;&lt;p&gt;So much this evening!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We started with standing &amp;amp; shifting our weight up over our feet, rather than standing on our toes. Several things happened: first off, folk leaning forwards over their feet, but leaving their heels behind so that their weight moved forward in their body &amp;amp; they lost stability. Also, moving their One Point forward ahead of the rest of the body, producing an arch in the lower back which is a point of weakness. Also, there's a lot of "noise" in the legs when standing on our toes. There's less "noise" when rising by shifting our weight forwards. Important to notice that there is still noise - things are still happening in the feet and legs, so we aren't standing still so much as allowing useful movement within the system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On to &lt;em&gt;ikkyo-undo&lt;/em&gt; two ways (&lt;em&gt;zengo-undo&lt;/em&gt;). It seems that when folk put their feet in positions, stability is compromised. However, when movement originates at the One Point, and the feet just find their place under the hip joints, stability remains.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally, a study of 5th form &lt;em&gt;kokyunage&lt;/em&gt;, which incorporates &lt;em&gt;zengo-undo&lt;/em&gt;. It's an exercise which shows up the difference between rule of mind (down is down!) and rule of body (limbs arc as they move). It's also a great exercise for relying on correct form to disrupt the &lt;em&gt;uke&lt;/em&gt;'s balance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was much head-scratching tonight, but sometimes that's a good thing!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;#itaintwhatyoudoitsthewaythatyoudoit&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>