<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/moduleshttps://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Falling uphill</title><description>Personal thoughts on hills, aikido, and falling</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/</link><image><url>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/favicon.png</url><title>Falling uphill</title><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/</link></image><generator>Ghost 3.2</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2020 16:27:16 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title>Kevin Saunders RIP</title><description>&lt;p&gt;I heard, this afternoon, of another one passing. Not an aikidoka this time, but someone equally interested in the mindbody moving, and with great sensitivity too. I looked up his Facebook timeline to see whether there had been any forewarning of illness, but instead found this: &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/notes/yoga-ground/street-food-alexander-for-lifting-heavy-suitcases/10156662613673270/"&gt;carrying heavy luggage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Two&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/kevin-saunders-rip/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5ce42c6856238709cab34a57</guid><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2020 16:13:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content/images/2020/02/portrait_400x400.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content/images/2020/02/portrait_400x400.jpg" alt="Kevin Saunders RIP"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I heard, this afternoon, of another one passing. Not an aikidoka this time, but someone equally interested in the mindbody moving, and with great sensitivity too. I looked up his Facebook timeline to see whether there had been any forewarning of illness, but instead found this: &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/notes/yoga-ground/street-food-alexander-for-lifting-heavy-suitcases/10156662613673270/"&gt;carrying heavy luggage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Two things struck me: (i) how we all carry heavy luggage of one sort or another, and (ii) how we all tend to freeze momentarily when attempting to improve our approach.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kevin says that carrying luggage involves timing, distraction, load, and coordination, and lists the ways we are thwarted in these elements.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The relevance of what he's saying to Aikido is impossible to miss. We have to negotiate timing, load and distraction, whilst hoping to respond in a coordinated and artful manner. No small task!&lt;/p&gt;<https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content:encoded></item><item><title>Public and private lessons</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Omote &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;Ura&lt;/em&gt; are a pair of words generally translated as &lt;em&gt;front&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;back&lt;/em&gt;, i.e. they depend on physical location and relationships to one another. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They are used to describe the nage's movement in relation to the uke – &lt;em&gt;omote&lt;/em&gt; passing across the front of the uke, &lt;em&gt;ura&lt;/em&gt; passing behind.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/public-and-private-lessons/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5e551ab5a6d94b09a49ee54c</guid><category>Aikido</category><category>Class Notes</category><category>principles</category><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2020 15:35:07 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content/images/2020/02/zeninmotion.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content/images/2020/02/zeninmotion.jpg" alt="Public and private lessons"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Omote &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;Ura&lt;/em&gt; are a pair of words generally translated as &lt;em&gt;front&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;back&lt;/em&gt;, i.e. they depend on physical location and relationships to one another. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They are used to describe the nage's movement in relation to the uke – &lt;em&gt;omote&lt;/em&gt; passing across the front of the uke, &lt;em&gt;ura&lt;/em&gt; passing behind. On some occasions, I have heard them used in place of &lt;em&gt;irimi&lt;/em&gt; (entering) and &lt;em&gt;tenkan (turning)&lt;/em&gt; though I think there are specific differences  between the pairs that make this less useful.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So that is the generally understood Aikido usage – to refer to positioning.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, there is another reading of front/back which gives rise to public/private, open/secret, visible/invisible – that allows us to find &lt;em&gt;omote&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;ura&lt;/em&gt; anywhere we care to look on the mat. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For example, I had the opportunity to attend a course taught by a senior teacher recently. He was teaching a range of grades, and leading the students through the various points he wished to highlight.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was his uke for the duration and, as a result, experienced at first hand what he was talking about. More importantly, I experienced what he was not talking about, what was not highlighted for the class. That which was said was inevitably a reduced selection of that which was available to me. There were, in effect, two lessons taking place – the &lt;em&gt;omote&lt;/em&gt; lesson of the teacher instructing, and the &lt;em&gt;ura&lt;/em&gt; lesson of his nervous system communicating directly to mine. Public and private, open and hidden, spoken and embodied.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Why is this worth mentioning? After all, given a moment to consider, we know that speech can be but a subsection of the greater experience. Because it should encourage us to lean further into the hidden depths of ukemi. That is where the learning really is.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I came across a harsh story (perhaps via Ellis Amdur) of horses that highlights what I'm getting it. The horse that is already responsive learns nothing from its owner; the horse that needs leading learns more, more deeply; but the nag that needs whipping to do anything is the greatest treasure because that horse learns down to its very bones how to behave. I'm not one for whipping animals, so this makes an unpleasant story, but ... for our purposes, if we want our study of aikido to penetrate down to our very bones, then we should seek to learn via every mode possible. Not just &lt;em&gt;omote&lt;/em&gt; verbal instructions, but those &lt;em&gt;ura &lt;/em&gt;instructions that simply can't be verbalised.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm not talking about verbal instructions that teachers choose to withhold, but those instructions that are secret even to them – the lessons that their bodies make available.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If we only look for what is visible, we will never see the invisible. If we only listen for what is said, we'll never hear what is left unsaid.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I teach, I spend little time on ukemi beyond ensuring that ukes know how to move in order to stay safe. I often think I should talk more about it, tell them how to follow, what to look for, what mindset to have. But after this recent course, I think that ukemi (beyond staying safe) is and should remain an &lt;em&gt;ura&lt;/em&gt; domain, one not spoken of, but revealed solely through experience.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Perhaps all I could say of it is: lean in, give it your attention, open your eyes, your hands, your heart.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: html--&gt;&lt;ol class="smaller"&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;"Omote (the public face) and ura (the private face) are twin concepts that are applied to almost any aspect of Japan or life in Japan.", in &lt;a href="https://www.nakasendoway.com/omote-ura-public-and-private-faces/"&gt;Omote-ura – Public and Private Faces&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;'When applied to Japan geographically, the east side is the &lt;em&gt;omote&lt;/em&gt; because it is the face of Japan that everyone knows about, particularly in the case of foreigners. On the other hand, the west side is the &lt;em&gt;ura&lt;/em&gt;, the so-called “inner Japan,” which people, including both foreigners and those who live on the omote side, usually do not come into contact with at all', &lt;em&gt;Benjamin Liu&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;a href="https://berkleycenter.georgetown.edu/posts/omote-ura-at-the-heart-of-zen-buddhism-in-the-mountains-of-western-japan"&gt;Omote-Ura: At the Heart of Zen Buddhism in the Mountains of Western Japan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;'The implications for Japanese psychological functioning of the inter-relationships of two concepts familiar to Japanese are discussed: omote, literally “face” is the pattern one would show to others; ura, “mind” in old Japanese, those private and intimate thoughts which generally are not to be shown to others', &lt;em&gt;Doi L Takeo&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;a href="https://journals.lww.com/jonmd/Abstract/1973/10000/Omote_and_Ura__Concepts_Derived_From_the_Japanese.5.aspx"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;"When we read a foreign language, we are really thinking in our own language most of the time", &lt;em&gt;Suzuki Tadao&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/132001?read-now=1&amp;seq=3#page_scan_tab_contents"&gt;Omote (Explicit) and Ura (Implicit): Translating Japanese Political Terms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-end: html--&gt;<https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content:encoded></item><item><title>Loch Falloch</title><description>&lt;p&gt;I had been up this road before so I knew not to believe the sign that said “Unsuitable for Motor Vehicles.” &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was a narrow single-track tarmac’d lane in the Highlands. I remembered it from wanders as a young boy about 40 years ago. Of course it had changed;&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/loch-falloch/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5cbb0d973ac1ce08a8af33ea</guid><category>Walking</category><category>magic</category><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2019 13:09:58 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content/images/2019/04/michael-podger-203447-unsplash.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content/images/2019/04/michael-podger-203447-unsplash.jpg" alt="Loch Falloch"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I had been up this road before so I knew not to believe the sign that said “Unsuitable for Motor Vehicles.” &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was a narrow single-track tarmac’d lane in the Highlands. I remembered it from wanders as a young boy about 40 years ago. Of course it had changed; what I recollected as open moorland had grown up until the wealth of trees and bushes shaded the track and blocked the view. After a short drive along, now bounded by high deer fences, I found the reason for the sign at the entrance to the road. Whether by subsidence or over-growth on the roadside, the moor had turned to marsh and the tarmac had slipped under a long pool of deep peaty-brown water. I tried to walk along the edges to prod the depths, but couldn’t get close to the middle of the water as the marsh was claiming me with some hunger. Instead, I returned to my car, wound the window down and proceeded with some concern. The car slid slowly downwards and then levelled off, giving me an early sense of relief, just before – I guessed, because I certainly couldn’t see – deep potholes dropped the car several inches lower. Involuntarily, my eyes flicked back inside the car to see whether the water was finding its way into the footwell. There was another sudden, deeper drop before the car finally emerged, dripping like a soggy sheep from its dip.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I drove on. I was looking for some sense of familiarity along the road – expecting a track off to the right , another opposite it to the left, and the shell of an old croft-house above the road. I drove past a track on the right, unconfirmed by the other signs, but returned to it when it became clear that I had gone too far with no other indicators. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Parking just before the track, I noticed a reed screen at the rise just above the road so took my binoculars up to it. A small placard suggested that black grouse may be nesting on the moor beyond the screen. I looked, saw nothing, but lingered even so. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have been curious about magic for as long as I can remember. Not the conjurors and prestidigitators of 70s TV or Las Vegas shows, but the real stuff – the magic that thins the veil between my daily preoccupations and the glory of universal creation. In retrospect, this day was a magical day – of a dozen little coincidences that, considered together, carried meaning. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: html--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name="cite-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;So I waited at the screen, not wanting to give up on the grouse or dismiss them. This moment of waiting was a pause spent looking through a doorway into another world. To my tired eyes, it was just more moorland – the same as on the other side of the road, as extended for miles in all directions; at the same time, this screen offered the promise that there was another truth also hidden here – that this was a site of great importance and interest, and that, if I stood patiently on one side of this screen, an invisible curtain would lift to reveal its precious secret. So, here I stood, by a screen 12 feet long, the land either side of it identical in flora and fauna. I could walk around either side, remain in the same world&lt;sup&gt;[&lt;a href="#fn-1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/sup&gt;, and see nothing. Or, quietly and patiently, I could watch through the screen and wait.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-end: html--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: html--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name="cite-2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Whilst I stood, voyeur-in-waiting, a couple of cars pulled up and six women emerged chatting in the clearing several yards to one side and down from the screen. I felt foolish huddled against it in clear view. They could see beyond the screen just as well as me, or even better without the line drawn by the frame. But they couldn’t see through the screen; without the curtain between them and the beyond, they couldn’t witness its lifting. There, almost silently, from left to right, flew a male black grouse visible only to me through the holes in the screen. Black wings, with bright white patches, red eyebrows, and tightly curved black tail feathers. Flying to the glory of god&lt;sup&gt;[&lt;a href="#fn-2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/sup&gt;. Flying to deliver satori to me. A flash of magic, and then immediate return to the mundane: just a man, standing close beside a reed screen in the middle of a moor, with a cluster of women chatting nearby. I turned and walked away quietly, my heart burst open by the secret that I, and only I, had been given. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-end: html--&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rather than follow the track and pass close by the women, which would have required mutual acknowledgement and interaction, I stepped off across the heather with the aim of meeting the trail again further on. Within a few paces, Nature stopped me again – just above the ground, a white ermine moth clung to a heather stalk. An utterly brilliant white, with black threads running across its wings and black eye patches and eyebrows. Another pause, another hint that magic is all around us in the mundane. The black grouse had cracked something open in me; the white ermine moth invited me to look yet more closely: &lt;em&gt;god is in the details&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I recovered the trail – an old landrover track, two large wheel ruts with a high grass verge running in the middle. As I followed its winding curves, something felt familiar but at such a deep level inside me that I could point to nothing, recognise nothing, remember nothing. But somewhere deep inside me, almost untouchably deep, was a feeling that this track was right. All the change and growth of close to a half century between my last visit and today meant that not one thing sparked conscious familiarity, but the felt sense was still ever so quietly there. I came to a high new deer fence with large wooden gate, still smelling of freshly cut pinewood, with a sign that this work had been paid for by the European Union in order to safeguard indigenous highland woodland. I knew to go through. Clambering over a second gate, this time a five-bar farm gate, I saw the shell of a two-storey crofthouse, now just window-less stone walls and dangerously-leaning gable ends. Later, I recognised it as the croft I had been looking for beside the road, misplaced in my memory. Near it, an old steading barn, with a rusted corrugated tin roof, wrapped in nettles. I didn’t recognise this building. Until, that is, I wandered over a small rise and saw some ewes with their lambs in the lea of the barn. Immediately another invisible curtain was lifted, from entirely unknown, unrecognised and mundane, to a secret place full of meaning, marking the entrance to my magic world of childhood. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Without the sheep, an almost derelict outhouse on a grassy patch between woodland and braes; with the sheep, the doorway to a tunnel through time, a lintel telling me silently that I’m finally home. Around me the peculiar gradients of grassy rises and dips, the yellows and greens of gorse and broom, the particular smell of sheep, all became landing lights guiding me inwards. This neglected, unvisited country was sighing and gathering itself for me, preparing to re-tell stories of long ago, to weave me back into its and my past, to weave a tapestry of past, present, and future, of sheep, heather, cuckoo, of laughter, rowing, fishing, picnicking, of a mundane early afternoon’s mizzle and the magic of the lens of remembrance that wound gossamer memories between the bushes, a lochan where now there’s only a burn winding through grass, trout nibbling at our flies tickling the surface of the water, a boathouse with an old wooden rowboat with rowlocks and oars stashed inside. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The magic was all around me and within me – a sense of completeness in this place, a sense of belonging in time and place together. I experienced aches and pains in my heart, turnings in my belly, every breath drew place in and history out – the magic of place as meaning, of the gift I received less through memories of the past, but of present sensations arising from so deep within that they could have been without. Where, in this small world, do I end and surroundings begin? To experience such visceral knowing, comfort and sense of rightful placement so far below the level of memories, stories, words, thoughts, speech, is to be person and place entwined together, person completed by place, hole made whole. To walk around the shores of the dried-up lochan was to press upon the thin soils until they released their particular scents, and their memories of me, a once small boy, youngest in a family spanning three generations gathered at Grandpa’s Loch for a picnic and a spot of fishing. And each step along the edges also pressed something up into me, an urgent, insistent message from the earth to the humus breathed alive: you are home, you are welcome, you have been missed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: html--&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a name="fn-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;I am reminded of C.S. Lewis describing a similar doorwary in his final tale of Narnia, &lt;i&gt;The Last Battle&lt;/i&gt;, which one could walk all around and see nothing, but by walking through could enter a other world entirely of one's deserving (or of one's god's grave). &lt;a href="#cite-1"&gt; &amp;uarr; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a name="fn-2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;"glory of god", "glory of universal creation" – insert your own euphemism here ... in case it's not obvious, I'm struggling to find a usable wording for my sense of the Whole That's Greater Than The Sum Of The Parts. &lt;a href="#cite-2"&gt; &amp;uarr; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-end: html--&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;My mother once told me a story that took place on the brae above Loch Falloch. Her brother, my uncle, was in the painful late stages of an unhappy marriage. One afternoon, he walked off by himself. Above the loch, he sat looking out over the moorland. There, a Highland gentleman joined him, garbed in the clothes of a couple of centuries previously. They sat together and talked with each other, Ian speaking English, his visitor responding in old Gaelic. The old man stayed awhile, before making his farewell, and disappeared so suddenly that Ian could not follow his steps, leaving my uncle without a shred of doubt that he had been a ghost of the braes returned to help him process his pain. For me, this is not (yet another) folksy ghost tale from the Highlands. Rather it is a reminder of how little we can perceive with our normal senses, and perhaps an indicator of just how intertwined we are with Existence, if we are just able to open to it (most often accomplished via pain, sorrow, or distress)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;I think there are some key elements to this day that came together to create conditions conducive to what I’m calling magic. First of all, though, what do I mean by magic? Through the Middle Ages, people saw the world primarily as a garment they wore rather than a collection of discrete objects they confronted. Yet the mimetic tradition was severely attenuated from Plato’s time on, and it was chiefly the alchemical and magical tradition that attempted to demonstrate how limited this objectivity was.  "Hermetic wisdom” was dedicated to the notion that real knowledge occurred only via the union of subjectivity &amp;amp; objectivity. In general, mediaeval life and thought were significantly affected by animistic and Hermetic notions, and to some extent can discussed as a unified consciousness (from Morris Berman’s &lt;em&gt;The Re-enchantment of the World&lt;/em&gt;) The elements:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;I drove eastwards for an hour and a half before arriving in the area of Loch Falloch. Much of that drive was through rain, on twisty and slippery roads. Therefore, I took my time. Other drivers overtook me regularly. Even after the rain had stopped, the roads had dried and straightened out, I continued slowly. Not rushing became a deliberate part of the journey.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;I avoided people as much as possible that day - talking only briefly to the monumental stone mason inscribing my mother’s headstone, and once to my wife to tell her I was soon on my way home.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;My phone died fairly early in the day - it was with me long enough to take photos around the loch, for which I’m grateful, but then gave up. It was my only form of time-keeping that day, as the car clock was also on the blink, so I had to judge time by its passing, or simply let go of any possible time constraints and allow myself to wander from place to place and task to task as my mood required.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;I was in an area very rich in personal folklore. Although my family’s presence in that area only goes back to the 1950s, I’m now introducing a fourth generation to our stories and histories located there.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;It was a day of strong feeling. I had called to chivvy the stone mason the afternoon before, and learned that he had forgotten my job. It felt like I was neglecting my mother’s memory, and that she couldn’t fully rest there until her name was on the stone. I couldn’t invite others to visit before this job was complete. There was sadness, longing, joy, and a whole host of other emotions vying for my attention through the day.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;<https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content:encoded></item><item><title>Levels of training</title><description>&lt;h2 id="training-for-what"&gt;Training, for what?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;What is the purpose of aikido? Take all the fun stuff away, and what are you left with? &lt;em&gt;Aikido is training to develop freedom within constraint&lt;/em&gt;. Both physical freedom from movement habits, stiffnesses, tensions; and mental freedom from emotional and psychological habits, habits of perspective, and so&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/levels-of-training/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5c9cce079c442616b52d60db</guid><category>Aikido</category><category>Class Notes</category><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 29 Mar 2019 00:04:36 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content/images/2019/03/cyrus-lopes-322512-unsplash.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;h2 id="training-for-what"&gt;Training, for what?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content/images/2019/03/cyrus-lopes-322512-unsplash.jpg" alt="Levels of training"&gt;&lt;p&gt;What is the purpose of aikido? Take all the fun stuff away, and what are you left with? &lt;em&gt;Aikido is training to develop freedom within constraint&lt;/em&gt;. Both physical freedom from movement habits, stiffnesses, tensions; and mental freedom from emotional and psychological habits, habits of perspective, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Without freedom, we are reactive towards our constraints, either &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; them or &lt;em&gt;away&lt;/em&gt; from them. With freedom, we can allow our constraints to exist but not be constrained by them. If that sounds contradictory, so be it!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To bring these training levels to life, we're going to look at &lt;em&gt;raising hands above head and bending&lt;/em&gt;, though likely just the raising hands bit. Also, although in ki testing we have someone doing the exercise and someone testing, I'll stick to the aikido roles of &lt;em&gt;nage&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;uke&lt;/em&gt; to indicate the person studying and the person testing respectively.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="level1"&gt;Level 1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first level of training is where we learn to coordinate mind and body (testing &lt;em&gt;ki&lt;/em&gt;). It is far more than the simply-phrased principles would suggest:– we need to remove holding, stiffening, tension, and habits from the body, and their equivalents in the mind.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Level 1 seeks to develop clear communication between mind and body. Therefore, much &lt;em&gt;ki testing&lt;/em&gt; is level 1 – the mind learns to give clear direction to the body, and the body to execute that precisely.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can test for level 1 alone or with a uke's involvement. The uke can watch the nage raise their hands, and then test forwards through the back or downwards at the raised wrists; or the uke can hold the wrists at the start and follow the movement to test it throughout. The test is just enough to find the nage's state, rather than to pressure-test it (&lt;em&gt;can you feel stability?&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;how much stability can you feel?)&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At this level, the uke does not have an opinion, she is just standing coordinated with a willingness to move; she does not add her own spice to the mix!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In an aikido exercise, this means the uke's role for the nage is to move without judgement, simply to make visible the communication between nage's mind and body. For their own part, the uke's job is to develop awareness, sensitivity, responsiveness, and being continually present.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nage's aim is to give direction to their body with their mind. It sounds simple. It really isn't when there's another person on the end of the movement. As nage, I watch to see if my uke is going where I want them to. If they are not, I tend to try to move them when what I need to do at level 1 is correct my movement. So, it's important to see the effect on the uke, and then return oneself to correct one's own movement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id="level-2"&gt;Level 2&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now the nage's aim is to give direction to their uke's body with their own mind (testing &lt;em&gt;jin/kokyu&lt;/em&gt;). Assuming that they are regularly achieving level 1, this means learning to extend their mind further.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the exercise, the uke now holds the wrists &lt;em&gt;with a downwards feeling&lt;/em&gt;, and seeks to maintain that feeling throughout. The nage may react against that feeling, seeking to drive their way through, but that will be unstable (as in their internal equilibrium is lost, if not their balance). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the exercise is done at level 2, the uke should feel their arms raised even though their mind maintains that downwards intention.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In an aikido exercise, the uke now projects their intention in a certain direction, but finds that they cannot move in that direction because their body is being deflected, drawn another way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id="level-3"&gt;Level 3&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;At this point, the nage's aim is to direct the uke's mind with their mind, so that the uke's mind directs their body in the wrong direction. This is mis-direction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Therefore, in the ki exercise, the uke should hold the wrists with a downwards feeling, but discover that they've lost that feeling as the nage moves. A common experience is for the uke to ask to do it again because they weren't paying attention. If, in fact, they were paying attention but then lost it, the likelihood is that the nage has successfully moved their mind from its focus.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id="etiquette"&gt;Etiquette&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;We say that there should be little communication between partners practising together, and nothing in the way of feedback or correction offered. Why so?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Communication patterns are habitual. Correction is more often the result of habitual patterns of thinking than actually based directly on the experience. For example, most people would either correct the other each time, or correct themselves each time. That is simply a reflection of whether they tend to take too much responsibility or too little for events as they unfold.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nage and uke, tested and tester, together make up the exercise, but most of us are attending to only one half of that combination. If I continually correct myself, I am ignoring what you're doing; if I continually correct you, I am neglecting my own effect.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The simplest thing to do is keep quiet and let the event be experienced by the body without comment. Direct experience of this sort is always richer than judgement or commentary, even if it isn't particularly obvious to our conscious mind. Rest assured that what needs to be learnt is being learned through our bodily senses, and that that will percolate into our mind in due time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id="another-exercise"&gt;Another exercise&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nage offers his wrists out (for 9th form), and the uke places his hands on the wrists (not holding or grasping). This is an exercise for the uke, so the uke will be working through the three levels outlined above.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id="level-0"&gt;Level 0&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nage steps forwards (or back), and the uncoordinated uke is buffeted to (or fro).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id="level-1"&gt;Level 1&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This time, the uke seeks to move seemless with the nage. If the nage moves backwards and contact is lost, the uke has failed. If the nage moves forwards, and the pressure of contact increases, the uke has failed. The uke is aiming to move precisely with the nage, so that the pressure does not alter in the slightest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the uke's mind attending to the nage, and then giving precise instruction to the body to move.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id="level-2-1"&gt;Level 2&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This time, the uke extends his mind further into the nage. If he was making contact at the wrist earlier, now he is reaching towards the One Point through the wrist. This time, when the uke moves with the nage, the likelihood is that the nage is de-stabilised, because the penetration of the uke's mind into nage's body is deeper, and therefore the uke is directing the real movement of the nage. The nage's intention to move forward stays constant throughout this, but their body doesn't quite seem to obey so well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id="level-3-1"&gt;Level 3&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This time, the uke reaches to the One Point and holds it – just with their mind. When the nage attempts to move, they find they are stuck, thwarted from the outset. Their mind is moved so that their efforts to move are lost, switched off, before they begin.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;h3 id="ken-yu-shin"&gt;Ken - Yu - Shin&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;A three-level categorisation of skill used by O Sensei from a general set of principles that have been extant for many centuries: &lt;em&gt;ken&lt;/em&gt; (manifest), &lt;em&gt;yu&lt;/em&gt; (hidden/subtle), &lt;em&gt;shin&lt;/em&gt; (divine).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ken&lt;/em&gt; (level 1) is power and finesse (i.e. self-control).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yu&lt;/em&gt; (level 2) is finding, moment by moment, the opponent's points of instability and taking advantage of them. This level is also considered a harmonisation of hard and soft.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shin&lt;/em&gt; (level 3) relies far less on physical power or leverage, and instead affects the will and the physical energy of the opponent.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(from Ellis Amdur's &lt;em&gt;Hidden in Plain Sight&lt;/em&gt;, 2nd ed., 2018)&lt;/p&gt;<https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content:encoded></item><item><title>One Point as authority</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Any martial art has associated etiquette. We may think that we follow it because it's an essential part of the tradition, but we are not Japanese, nor are we studying a particularly Japanese form of aikido. In fact, our organisation has minimised the amount of etiquette, yet what we have,&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/one-point-as-authority/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5c8eae7096cc581288cbd5e7</guid><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2019 14:46:05 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Any martial art has associated etiquette. We may think that we follow it because it's an essential part of the tradition, but we are not Japanese, nor are we studying a particularly Japanese form of aikido. In fact, our organisation has minimised the amount of etiquette, yet what we have, we hold preciously.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One obvious example of this is that partners working together should not offer feedback on each other. That is akin to teaching, and "there is only one teacher on the mat".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, here's my question: how do we learn to improve without feedback on what we have just done? Why does etiquette seem to discourage such communication?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the first instance, I think it's useful to take a view on what role etiquette really performs – it's surely not just anachronistic other-culture imitation, is it? A bunch of rules from another place and another time followed either to catch us out or to make us feel more like the warriors we imagine ye olde samurai to have been?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The purpose of aikido is to develop our ability to be free under constraint&lt;/em&gt;, to move and think freely (and therefore truly independently) under pressure. It's very clear how that pressure manifests in the physical realm: our partner holds us, and we seek to move fluidly with minimal effort.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the physical context is just one part of the process; the other is freedom of the mind. Arguably, this freedom of mind – to think and feel without getting caught up by those thoughts and emotions – is primary. Without a clear mind we cannot have a free body. If our mind is working in opposition or reaction to incoming pressures, our body will also be oppositional. We use the phrase &lt;em&gt;fighting mind&lt;/em&gt; to denote such oppositional patterns of thought and behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I believe that etiquette performs a similar role for the mind that our partner's grasp does for the body. Etiquette constrains us whilst inviting us to find real, meaningful freedom within such constraints. Over time, as we develop our freedom under pressure, so we gain real freedom with or without pressure – freedom of movement (a natural body) and freedom of mind (a creative, non-reactive, wise mind).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Back to the injunction that partners should not give each other feedback.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Well, what happens when we do? My partner throws me skilfully, and I say that they did well. I have validated their effort, and in so doing I have made myself the authority in that relationship. If they struggle and I kindly offer advice, I have affirmed that the mistake is theirs and I have made myself the authority in that relationship. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And what about my development? If I am watching and commenting upon their movements, there is likely little room for me to attend to my own development. We are equals in the relationship of an exercise, and we both have a vital role to play. If we are both watching the work of the &lt;em&gt;nage&lt;/em&gt;, the thrower, then who is ensuring the development of the &lt;em&gt;uke&lt;/em&gt;, the thrown? If I am &lt;em&gt;uke&lt;/em&gt;, my focus needs to be on my role. Of course I will have opinions about my partner's performance, but since I am providing the all-important constraints, I should really attend to that task alone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So much for the etiquette, what about the feedback? If my partner offers no response, where can I find an authoritative view of my movement?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="enter-the-one-point"&gt;Enter the One Point&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;If there is no-one around us who can speak to our experience, we might look within ourselves for that feedback. The One Point is both viscera that moves and is moved, and also Center (physically, of gravity; somatically, of our being) that intuits and communicates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="a-story"&gt;A story&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have heard that my teacher's teacher, Abbe Kenshiro Sensei, would grunt whenever asked a question. I imagine that, at first, people thought he was working out how to reply in what was to him a foreign language, but eventually he was asked why he grunted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I make that sound in order to send the question to my One Point, to ensure that my reply comes from the whole of me.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That might sound strange, but we had a young baby-sitter for a while who I would ask &lt;em&gt;how are you?&lt;/em&gt; and she would reply &lt;em&gt;fine, thanks, how are you?&lt;/em&gt; so quickly that it felt like bullets spitting from a machine gun. Over time, as she grew more comfortable with us, she would take longer to begin her reply, and tell us far more than &lt;em&gt;fine, thanks&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id="another-story"&gt;Another story&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;I attended a series of conferences, each of which ended with a circle in which everyone would speak when they were ready in order to complete their attendance. I noticed that I tended to be one of the last to speak, and decided to sneak my words in earlier.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, each time someone spoke, I listened and then sat momentarily to let their words settle in me. By the time I was ready to speak, someone else had already started talking. I noticed two things: the first was that the person who was determined to speak next wouldn't be listening to the speaker before them – they were already sounding the words in their head – and, secondly, what they had to say had no connection to what had been said before – it existed independently of everyone else.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I spoke, finally, I often had no idea what I was going to say, and started with &lt;em&gt;I'm not sure what to say but ...&lt;/em&gt; and then the words would come out fluently, taking me by surprise. I also received feedback that what I said summed the event up for everyone, not just for myself.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I believe that I was speaking from my One Point. By letting others' words percolate down into my Center, I mixed them with mine, and what came back out combined the different threads more effectively.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The response of the other participants was that I spoke with authority. Which is hard to square with the sense that I didn't know what I was going to say, until I allow the possibility of my One Point being the authority, rather than my verbal, thinking mind.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By allowing experiences all the way into the One Point, they pass through the head (thinking), the heart (feeling), and to the gut (intuition), and so those different but complementary elements are combined in my response. What better authority could we have to assess any experience?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And so, back to aikido etiquette. Perhaps we are not being left all alone to figure stuff out, so much as being invited to find that place within ourselves that can combine all the different aspects of our experience and create a deeper response to them. Perhaps, instead of asking for feedback from those that provide the constraints, we can learn to listen to the authority that is within us.&lt;/p&gt;<https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content:encoded></item><item><title>The Heart Point</title><description>&lt;p&gt;I have referred to the One Point regularly through these posts, but that's not its full name. More properly, it is the Lower One Point. Lower, because there are three, the Upper One Point in the head, the Middle One Point in the heart area, and the Lower One Point&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/the-heart-point/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5c90ea15406a2506ec1723cf</guid><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2019 13:47:40 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content/images/2019/03/nick-fewings-532590-unsplash.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content/images/2019/03/nick-fewings-532590-unsplash.jpg" alt="The Heart Point"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have referred to the One Point regularly through these posts, but that's not its full name. More properly, it is the Lower One Point. Lower, because there are three, the Upper One Point in the head, the Middle One Point in the heart area, and the Lower One Point in the belly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Because of its physicality, the Lower One Point is considered more important than the other two in martial arts, so is usually referred to as just the One Point.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Remembering this, I decided to take my dog for a walk from the Middle One Point – my Heart Point (yep, I just coined this phrase and it feels great).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For a long time, I would move from my (lower) One Point by letting that part of my body go first, drawing the rest of me along behind it. Can you imagine that? My belly would bulge forwards, my lower back would arch, and eventually the rest of me would follow. Unsurprisingly, it did not provide me either the strength or connectedness that I was hoping for.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eventually, I tried keeping my One Point in place and moving the whole of me from that point. In other words, moving as one unit. Ah, there was the strength, there was the connectedness.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, today, when I attempted to walk from my Heart Point, I did not consciously push my chest out or contract the space between my shoulder blades. I stayed as one unit, and simply let my attention rest at my heart as I moved.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In terms of physical movement, I became aware of my upper torso turning and swaying slightly, in an unencumbered fashion. I became aware of the rest of me &lt;em&gt;just moving&lt;/em&gt; seemingly without effort. By contrast, sometimes when I walk from my One Point I have a sense of driving myself forwards from that point.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But I was most aware of a particular physical sensation - a light ache in the area of my heart (the centre of my chest, rather than the left side of my chest where my muscular heart resides). That sensation was accompanied by a feeling of sadness, but sadness without specific cause so that it seemed to be an existential sadness.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Patior cogito sum (I suffer, therefore I am)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;I suffer, I endure&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;I allow, acquiesce, submit&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The combination of light heartache, sense of sadness, and free movement below made me feel very soft and gentle, inclined to tread lightly on this earth. My thoughts turned to suffering, compassion, kindness, and how they might &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; show up in the world.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If my quiet ache is indeed sadness, it appears without immediate cause. Therefore, I consider it existential – an inevitable part of the human condition. It takes practice to be comfortable with sadness; most of us seek either distraction away from it or to change and end it. But if this is indeed without cause, it has no beginning and thus no end. It just is. Learning to be with this sadness seems the sanest action one might take.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hence, compassion (&lt;em&gt;com + passio&lt;/em&gt;, lit. suffering with ...). If I can start by experiencing my sadness without seeking to change it, I am learning to be fully with myself (rather than just the happier bits). If I can recognise the inherent sadness of human nature, I can allow it to exist in others too, and I can learn to be with them in their sadness. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That is compassion:– being with others in their sadness, not seeking to change or end it, nor seeking to get away from it or them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In aikido training, we develop our One Point through exercises that allow us to find it first of all. We experience our One Point (almost passively) by allowing pressure from others to disperse through it. In time, we start to move from our One Point, using it in a more active way. We start by becoming aware of it, prior to using it; by learning to receive through it before acting from it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So too, I imagine, my Heart Point. Walking today, I was just trying to maintain my awareness of the state of my heart (or to retrieve that awareness once lost), to learn where it is and how it feels. Perhaps in the future, the work might become more outward and active – extending compassion to others, truly experiencing their pain, joy, doubt, excitement in my heart too.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What does this get me? Not sure yet. I imagine a softer, more precise aikido – one that can take in the wholeness of the person in front of me. I hope a more complete experience of life, both "good" bits and "bad" bits, comfortable and uncomfortable. I wish a more useful life, in which my wise, tender Heart Point is allowed to reach out and offer the small comfort to others that &lt;em&gt;we all suffer, and &lt;strong&gt;therefore we are&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;<https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content:encoded></item><item><title>Am I seeing things?</title><description>&lt;p&gt;I spent a few days studying with &lt;a href="http://wheelersystema.com/about-martin-wheeler/"&gt;Martin Wheeler&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href="http://www.russianmartialart.com/"&gt;Systema&lt;/a&gt; fame, something I would recommend to anyone. During that time, I had a few fascinating moments attacking him. Or, rather, attempting to. Perhaps the most interesting experience was when he seemed to disappear repeatedly as I attacked him.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/am-i-seeing-things/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5c7cf4d82529730a25aceb6a</guid><category>Aikido</category><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2019 12:36:47 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I spent a few days studying with &lt;a href="http://wheelersystema.com/about-martin-wheeler/"&gt;Martin Wheeler&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href="http://www.russianmartialart.com/"&gt;Systema&lt;/a&gt; fame, something I would recommend to anyone. During that time, I had a few fascinating moments attacking him. Or, rather, attempting to. Perhaps the most interesting experience was when he seemed to disappear repeatedly as I attacked him.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He would pop up in front of me, and then as my attention latched on to him and I moved, he disappeared. I would invariably find him behind me. It was astonishing. I have been trying to make head or tail of it ever since.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I think we are aware of others in two ways at once: through our vision and through our felt-sense. The latter relies on moments of meeting the other person, bumping into their tension, feeling the pull or push of their direction, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, when their tension doesn't exist, there's very little for our body to pick up on, even though we can see them. Our two systems collide, as they offer conflicting information to the brain. He's there – I can see him. No, he's not – because I can't feel him.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In our class, we study &lt;em&gt;ki development&lt;/em&gt; first, and then &lt;em&gt;aikido&lt;/em&gt;. Usually, the ki development exercise is something that can be studied or applied further in the aikido practice. Take, for example, the exercise known as &lt;em&gt;unbendable arm&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When we study this as a &lt;em&gt;ki&lt;/em&gt; exercise, we push gently upwards from below the wrist, and downwards through the elbow to see if the arm will bend. When the partner is incorrect, the arm bends. When the partner is correct, the arm bends enough to take up the slack, and then it stops despite increasing pressure. From the point of view of the tester, there is movement, and then there is none, and at that point, the tester feels the increasing compression of trying to move something that is immovable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As we move into this as part of an aikido exercise, however, we don't want to give the tester (now the &lt;em&gt;uke&lt;/em&gt;) the information that we are immovable. We don't want them to experience the increasing compression of pushing an unyielding arm. Therefore, we move. This is our choice, it is the result of an immovable mind. And it hides us from the &lt;em&gt;uke&lt;/em&gt;. We are not moving because the pressure of the push forces us; we are moving to remain invisible. We aim to be as responsive to our partner's touch as possible, so that they cannot gain a sense of where we are, of how light or heavy we are, of how pliant or stiff we are.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Therefore, during aikido, if our partner experiences the immovable nature of our unbendable arm, we have given ourselves away. Instead, they should feel the arm move in concert with them – to the extent that they couldn't say whether they are moving the arm or whether they are following the arm's movement. In other words, the action has become person-less.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I still don't know what Martin Wheeler did to achieve his invisibility, but this is my best guess. Complete relaxation, complete responsiveness, complete calmness. Whether I've got that right or not is moot, it's still a worthwhile path to explore.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;<https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content:encoded></item><item><title>Stretching between detail and feeling</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Last night was a revision evening - study through practice, rather than the usual breaking things down into steps and then putting them back together again.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;First form (&lt;em&gt;kosa-dori&lt;/em&gt;) &lt;em&gt;ikkyo, nikkyo, sankyo&lt;/em&gt; (I had the naive hope that we would get through more exercises than that).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have studied these&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/stretching-between-detail-and-feeling/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5c5d4d38a0c4080884514093</guid><category>Sankyo</category><category>1st form</category><category>Class Notes</category><category>Aikido</category><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2019 09:36:11 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content/images/2019/02/joshua-reddekopp-472467-unsplash.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content/images/2019/02/joshua-reddekopp-472467-unsplash.jpg" alt="Stretching between detail and feeling"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last night was a revision evening - study through practice, rather than the usual breaking things down into steps and then putting them back together again.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;First form (&lt;em&gt;kosa-dori&lt;/em&gt;) &lt;em&gt;ikkyo, nikkyo, sankyo&lt;/em&gt; (I had the naive hope that we would get through more exercises than that).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have studied these exercises in detail several times, which means paying close attention, which tends to mean going slowly and with small feeling.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recently, we spent a couple of evenings using the corner step to generate a big feeling, and learning how the exercise just falls into place when that big feeling is there.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last night was the occasion to put the two approaches together and practice – without too much teacherly interference.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What is very clear from this process is that &lt;em&gt;nikkyo&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;sankyo&lt;/em&gt; don't exist of themselves – they are responses to &lt;em&gt;ikkyo&lt;/em&gt; not completing successfully. Therefore, if one starts with the intention of doing &lt;em&gt;sankyo&lt;/em&gt; (for example), it won't go well. However, if one starts with &lt;em&gt;ikkyo&lt;/em&gt;, and then observes how it doesn't quite succeed, &lt;em&gt;sankyo&lt;/em&gt; becomes a useful next movement. This makes the &lt;em&gt;sankyo&lt;/em&gt; more effective, and less effort to set up.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We also saw that while a big feeling is great, it's not the be-all and end-all. It has to be combined with attention to detail, of course.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For example, holding someone in a standing &lt;em&gt;sankyo&lt;/em&gt; immobilisation is one thing. Throwing them downwards from that is something else. The trick is to notice how &lt;em&gt;sankyo&lt;/em&gt; affects the partner's centre of gravity (COG). &lt;em&gt;Sankyo&lt;/em&gt; tends to push the COG backwards in the body, so that their weight falls down to their heels (by contrast, &lt;em&gt;nikkyo&lt;/em&gt; draws the COG forwards in the body, so that the weight comes on to their toes).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If we apply &lt;em&gt;sankyo&lt;/em&gt; too strongly, the partner will simply step back to recover their COG (to centre it in their body). If we don't apply, the downwards throw will just be a yank on the arm. If we apply it just enough to encourage their COG backwards within their body, the downwards movement will require minimal effort.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;#wheresyourCOGtoday&lt;/p&gt;<https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content:encoded></item><item><title>In pursuit of magic</title><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;Any sufficiently advanced technology is indistinguishable from magic. ~ &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clarke%27s_three_laws"&gt;Arthur C. Clarke&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I would like to offer an aikido variation of Clarke's Third Law: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;any sufficiently subtle movement is indistinguishable from magic.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="whatwethinkmatters"&gt;What we think matters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wondered why the &lt;em&gt;up&lt;/em&gt; in press-ups and push-ups? Well, it's obvious, isn't&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/of-magic-and-other-technologies/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5c33663d2ac40f04a4902f15</guid><category>Aikido</category><category>magic</category><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 11:28:23 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content/images/2019/01/Quotefancy-6057232-3840x2160.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;blockquote&gt;Any sufficiently advanced technology is indistinguishable from magic. ~ &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clarke%27s_three_laws"&gt;Arthur C. Clarke&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content/images/2019/01/Quotefancy-6057232-3840x2160.jpg" alt="In pursuit of magic"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I would like to offer an aikido variation of Clarke's Third Law: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;any sufficiently subtle movement is indistinguishable from magic.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="whatwethinkmatters"&gt;What we think matters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wondered why the &lt;em&gt;up&lt;/em&gt; in press-ups and push-ups? Well, it's obvious, isn't it – we are moving our body upwards. Even so, the actual process involves pushing our hands &lt;em&gt;down&lt;/em&gt;, pushing the floor away from us. The extension through the arm moves our body upwards before the floor gives in, and hey presto!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If it's convenient, try this: get down into the bottom position of the press-up, and intend to push your body up. Go for it. Notice any tension that creeps in, and how much effort is involved. Now relax. Shake it off, if necessary. This time, intend to push the floor away from you, to push it further down into the ground, push your hands down. How much effort was involved there?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If your experience is anything like mine (it took a few goes before I could actually clearly think downwards) the actual exertion is much less than when doing a press-&lt;em&gt;up&lt;/em&gt;. It appears that&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;the body structures differently to lift the body up compared with pushing the floor down. Pushing the floor away seems to encourage a more relaxed body than trying to lift oneself up (also worth exploring with squats).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="amipushingorareyoufalling"&gt;Am I pushing, or are you falling?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can apply the same experiment to pushing a partner, from the side with a hand on their shoulder. Are we doing a push-&lt;em&gt;up &lt;/em&gt;and tightening ourselves to push them away, or are we doing a push-&lt;em&gt;down&lt;/em&gt; and just moving them away by extending our arm?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A clear intention matters because when I extend my mind to initialise the push, it creates the feeling that the push never occurred, but that the partner just fell away* and I followed. It seems that (a) my partner responds to the intention, and (b) my muscles don't trigger in an obvious way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: html--&gt;&lt;p class="smaller"&gt;[* I should add that, in this exercise, the partner is just standing without resistance. Of course, if I push him, he will move. What I'm interested in, here, is that he starts moving when I intend to push him – in other words, extending my mind starts him moving before I get the physical push going]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-end: html--&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I receive no physical feedback that I did it, and my partner receives no physical feedback that I did it, or that he did it by volunteering to fall away, then what are we left with?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Magic!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="youlllikeit"&gt;You'll like it,&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;And there we have it, &lt;em&gt;any sufficiently subtle movement is indistinguishable from magic&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="butnotalot"&gt;but not a lot.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another reason for calling it magic is that we can't necessarily re-create it directly – it seems really soft, but when I just try to be soft, nothing happens. All I can do is attempt to re-create the container within which the magic arises. That container is created by controlling myself – lightening my posture, relaxing, being centred and expansive – and connecting with my partner.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="andnowthetheory"&gt;And now, the theory&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;First of all, there are cells in the brain that map the body. They respond when the part of the body that they represent is touched, or when the eyes see something in close proximity to that part. Thus there is a bubble of near-space enclosing that body part – its peripersonal space. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Japan, in the late 90s, Dr. Atsushi Iriki wondered what happens to the brain's mapping of that peripersonal space when we are using tools. He taught monkeys to use rakes, wired their brains up in order to see the mind's map of the body, and sat back to see what happened.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was discovered the physical area that the cells mapped no longer extended just to the monkey's fingertips, but to the tip of the rake:– the monkey's brain was incorporating the tool into the animal's body schema. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"&gt;&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content/images/2019/01/monkey-rake-1.png" class="kg-image" alt="In pursuit of magic"&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;(a) Before learning to use a rake (left) or while passively holding the rake (right) without the intention of using it as a tool, the monkey’s hand-centered visual-tactile receptive fields stay confined to the hand’s immediate vicinity. But while the monkey is actively wielding the rake (center), the cells’ visual receptive fields expand along its length.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not just for monkeys, this ability to expand the mind's map of the body to include inanimate objects explains how we can reverse-park our car (hopefully with a fair degree of accuracy and skill), how we can hit tennis balls with a racquet, and work with any number of other tools.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In other words, "becoming one with" your tool is not a woo-woo mystical adage; it has a solid experiential and neuro-scientific underpinning.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"&gt;&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content/images/2019/01/monkey-rake-2.png" class="kg-image" alt="In pursuit of magic"&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;(b) The visual-tactile receptive field expansion of one of the monkey’s shoulder-centered neurons.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;In aikido, we want to replicate the magic or enhance it, and using partners and weapons can help with that. Just as the monkey had a rake, we have wooden training tools that serve to increase our reach. They, similarly, require moving with sensitivity and precision, and that requires purpose.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note that it is entirely possible to hold the bokken as a foreign object (see the third diagram in the first image) – which does not alter our mind mapping. What makes the difference is intention/purpose. In ki-aikido, we think along the length of the bokken, as if filling it with our spirit. Yes, that does sound strange, mystical, woo-woo, but now we're starting to see that it has a real purpose, a real effect. By unifying myself with the bokken, my brain is integrating the bokken into my body, allowing me to use it with greater precision and efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By working with weapons, we are encouraging our brain to expand its mapping of space around the body as peripersonal space. But that work has to be meaningful; we can't just wave the jo around randomly or to draw pretty arcs, we must know where we are deflecting, where we are striking at any point. That level of clarity makes the work real, which makes the jo part of us.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id="when-push-comes-to-shove-"&gt;When push comes to shove ...&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Back to the push: if I extend my mind in order to push my partner, perhaps my mind is incorporating my partner into my body schema as if they were part of my body. Thus there is no sense of pushing away a separate other, just extending oneself outwards.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="comestomove"&gt;... comes to move&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;But what about my partner's experience of not being pushed by me so much as just being moved? &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Being pushed and being moved do not have the same sensations. The sensation of movement is just that: movement. Someone can move us in plenty of ways: pushing, pulling, smiling, shouting, cajoling, inviting, brushing, and so on. Within all those there is information about the movement (sudden, effortless, etc) and about the instigator of the movement (he shoved me, she bumped me). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When we remove information about the instigator and their approach, we are just left with movement. My theory is that if the pusher extends their brain's map to include the pushee, it affects the pushee's experience so that they don't feel the push as an external force, at which point it becomes just movement (without a distinct source).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: html--&gt;&lt;p class="smaller"&gt;The quote in the main image points both to the ever-present risk of self-delusion – thinking I've got something when I got nuttin' – and to the risk of not daring to go beyond what &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; know. Both threaten our development; yet the line I choose to walk is right there, constantly threatening to over-balance one way or the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="smaller"&gt;If you &lt;em&gt;already know&lt;/em&gt; what aikido is, then you're welcome to laugh at my posts and move on. If you don't, then I invite you to investigate the ideas for yourself. Either you'll learn that I'm wrong (please, let me know!) or that there's more to investigate (please, let me know!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="smaller"&gt;The theory and diagrams come from &lt;em&gt;The Body Has a Mind of Its Own&lt;/em&gt; by Sandra Blakeslee and Matthew Blakeslee, published by Random House in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-end: html--&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: html--&gt;&lt;p class="smaller"&gt;An aside, but related. I go bouldering at our local centre, where many of the routes are sit-starts:– the starting holds are low enough that you sit on the floor to begin. When I sit and then start to climb, the initial movement is almost always effortful. When I move into the sit as if it's already part of the climb, moving upwards is easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class="smaller"&gt;I think that's the same magic on a number of levels: I am extending my mind, or not; I am already connected with the wall, or not; I am simply moving, or not.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-end: html--&gt;<https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content:encoded></item><item><title>States of Mind</title><description>&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;zanshin&lt;/em&gt;: continuous mind, extending mind,&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;mushin&lt;/em&gt;: no mind, &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;fudoshin&lt;/em&gt;: immovable mind, &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;shoshin&lt;/em&gt;: beginner's mind&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Blimey, where to begin?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ah, yes, obviously. Beginner's mind.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="beginnersmind"&gt;Beginner's Mind&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shoshin&lt;/strong&gt; (初心) is a word from &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zen_Buddhism"&gt;Zen Buddhism&lt;/a&gt; meaning "&lt;strong&gt;beginner's mind.&lt;/strong&gt;" It refers to having an attitude of openness, eagerness, and lack of preconceptions when&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/states-of-mind/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5c2de93c2ac40f04a4902e00</guid><category>Aikido</category><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 07 Jan 2019 13:55:33 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content/images/2019/01/felix-mittermeier-700255-unsplash.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;zanshin&lt;/em&gt;: continuous mind, extending mind,&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;mushin&lt;/em&gt;: no mind, &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;fudoshin&lt;/em&gt;: immovable mind, &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;shoshin&lt;/em&gt;: beginner's mind&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content/images/2019/01/felix-mittermeier-700255-unsplash.jpg" alt="States of Mind"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Blimey, where to begin?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ah, yes, obviously. Beginner's mind.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="beginnersmind"&gt;Beginner's Mind&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shoshin&lt;/strong&gt; (初心) is a word from &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zen_Buddhism"&gt;Zen Buddhism&lt;/a&gt; meaning "&lt;strong&gt;beginner's mind.&lt;/strong&gt;" It refers to having an attitude of openness, eagerness, and lack of preconceptions when studying a subject, even when studying at an advanced level, just as a beginner would. &lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;The phrase is also discussed in the book &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zen_Mind,_Beginner%27s_Mind"&gt;Zen Mind, Beginner's Mind&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shunryu_Suzuki"&gt;Shunryu Suzuki&lt;/a&gt;, a Zen teacher. Suzuki outlines the framework behind shoshin, noting "in the beginner's mind there are many possibilities, in the expert's mind there are few."&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shoshin#cite_note-1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; ~ &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shoshin"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unsurpisingly, Suzuki Sensei explains more clearly and pithily than I ever could. Beginner's mind is obviously an appropriate lens for learning; and the longer one studies, the more appropriate it is.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But what are we studying? &lt;em&gt;Aikido&lt;/em&gt; is a predominantly partner-based art, where each has a clear role. The partner exercises are actually &lt;em&gt;kata&lt;/em&gt;: prescribed forms that we aim to reproduce as precisely as possible, so that the principles of being and movement implicit within them become embodied within us. One of those principles is &lt;em&gt;continuous mind&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="continuousmind"&gt;Continuous mind&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Zanshin&lt;/em&gt; is the state of mind that we aim to possess throughout the kata. Eventually, it becomes our usual state of mind, so that it's no longer something we need to switch to. It is the state of relaxed awareness - complete awareness of one's surroundings, whilst being ready to respond without thought or notice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If one stands opposite one's partner and switches &lt;em&gt;on&lt;/em&gt;, it's already too late. If one throws a partner and then switches &lt;em&gt;off&lt;/em&gt;, we've missed the point. The idea of continuous mind is that it is always there, ready and aware. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, we don't talk about &lt;em&gt;continuing&lt;/em&gt; our mind, rather we prefer &lt;em&gt;extending&lt;/em&gt; our mind. It has the sense of outwardness and continuation, with the result of a continuing mind.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;“The right art … is purposeless, aimless! The more obstinately you try to learn how to shoot the arrow for the sake of hitting the goal, the less you will succeed …What stands in your way is that you think that what you do not do yourself does not happen,” ~ &lt;a href="https://mayooshin.com/zanshin-art-of-focus/"&gt;Kyudo (archery) Master Kenzo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="immovablemind"&gt;Immovable mind&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fudoshin&lt;/em&gt; is a state of equanimity or unpertubability. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Although wisdom is called immovable, this does not signify any insentient thing, like wood or stone. It moves as the mind is wont to move: forward or back, to the left, to the right, in the ten directions and to the eight points; and the mind that does not stop at all is called &lt;em&gt;immovable wisdom. ~ &lt;a href="https://budobum.blogspot.com/2015/03/states-of-mind-fudoshin.html"&gt;Takuan Soho&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;When something catches our attention, our mind is stopped by it. That it can be stopped is a sign that it is moveable. A mind that cannot be stopped, therefore, is immoveable. In Takuan's writing, immovable and unmoving are different. When your mind focuses on how your partner steps or raises a hand and then starts planning, rather than taking it in as part of a larger whole, then your mind has been moved.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;ki-aikido&lt;/em&gt;, we test for immovable mind using &lt;em&gt;ki tests&lt;/em&gt;. They are light tests of our basic structure. Not "can I push you off your spot?", but "what happens to your attention when I push lightly on you?"&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This sense of testing immovable mind allows for a moving body. Immovable mind does not equal immovable body. Rather the immovability of the mind is manifested in how the body moves in response to pressure – sometimes it is appropriate for the body to move, sometimes it is not.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="mushin"&gt;Mushin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;Literally meaning &lt;em&gt;no-mind&lt;/em&gt;, this is another linguistic puzzle. However, we can say with absolute certainty that no mind and mindlessness are not of the same ilk. Phew.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;No mind is a very quiet mind, one without preconception.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Be calm and let yourself see, hear and feel the entire situation. Instead of making a plan and figuring out what to do, just be there. When people talk about “no mind” the idea is to let the conscious, chattering, clutter of thoughts go and just be there. It’s not that you have no mind, but that you let go of the mile-a-minute constant chatter of unconsidered thought that modern life encourages and makes so difficult to escape. ~ &lt;a href="https://budobum.blogspot.com/2015/02/states-of-mind-mushin.html"&gt;The Budo Bum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This &lt;em&gt;no mind&lt;/em&gt; is a layer of our mind that comes before our verbal consciousness. It is just aware, it just knows, it just acts. Actions that come from this place tend to be very precisely, very minimal, very efficient, and very effective. And tend not to be experienced as anything &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; did, as &lt;em&gt;no mind&lt;/em&gt; operates before or below the ego (I think).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;All these states of mind! It is easy to get caught up by them and find your own mind whirring, never mind trying to move in concert with a pushy partner at the same time. There is only one technique in aikido, and that is the technique that can be taken out into every single aspect of life: &lt;em&gt;being awake&lt;/em&gt;. Anything is is either subsidiary to that or training for that. These states of mind are aspects of &lt;em&gt;being awake&lt;/em&gt;, and that is what real aikido is drilling into us. Not being able to do cool throws, not being able to wield a sword or staff fiercely, not looking good dressed in funky clothes. &lt;em&gt;Relaxed, open, alert, responsive and peaceful&lt;/em&gt;. That's the purpose of training; and, for the most part, that's the way to get through life.&lt;/p&gt;<https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content:encoded></item><item><title>The land welcomes you</title><description>Funny, I think – you've come here on holiday, and brought all your shit with you.</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/welcome-to-my-home/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5c2a60c0f2330941bcac3a8f</guid><category>Walking</category><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2019 00:27:32 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content/images/2018/12/burn-side-steps.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content/images/2018/12/burn-side-steps.jpg" alt="The land welcomes you"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Welcome to my home ...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have a couple of self-catering chalets on our 2-acre plot, which are usually fully booked for the spring and summer. That means we meet two new sets of strangers each week.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They come, often tired at the end of a long journey, to pick up the key. Or if we're out, we pop by to say hello when we return home. Either way, there is a moment of meeting for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I smile, introduce myself, and offer my hand.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The responses to that are &lt;em&gt;varied&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not everyone has taken my hand, though most do. Many take it and they look away; others shake it over an imaginary fence. Some barely touch it; others wring the life out of it. Yet others twist their wrist so that their hand holds mine down.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Funny, I think – you've come here on holiday, and brought all your shit with you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For them, I think, the relationship is transactional and necessary ("where should we collect the keys from?"). For us, it isn't, and that's what I want to explore.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When we moved here, looking at the huge oak and chestnut trees, wandering down to the river that has scoured seams of slate for millenia, studying the moss growing over a tumble-down rock wall, even looking at the rusted ironwork along the railway, I soon realised that we did not own this. If we insisted on putting ourselves at the centre, then we had become the stewards of this space, but that was still some human-centric stretch from the real feeling of the place.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We had become part of a landscape (though even that word is misleading), just as the moss growing on the wall, just as the bugs crawling under the moss and the buzzard hovering above it. &lt;em&gt;We belonged to it&lt;/em&gt;, not the other way round.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the English language at least, we put humans and human experience first. Subject - verb - object, every time. &lt;em&gt;I live here&lt;/em&gt;. Primacy for the human, all else relegated to background.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But that's not my experience.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Frank Forencich of Exuberant Animal writes of the&lt;em&gt; Long Body&lt;/em&gt; as human body intimately connected to habitat and tribe. Well, here we have both tribe – in our nuclear family and our paying guests – and we have habitat, the larger context within which we exist.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And I don't think our guests know that. They come, they holiday, they go. We stay, we welcome new strangers, we feel the differences between the holiday-makers from week to week, both face-to-face and through the feeling of the space of our property.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From Spring to mid-Autumn, there are short-stay strangers here most of the time. We may or may not see them daily, but they're present either physically or in our awareness. It is noticeable when the last guests of the year leave, and the human-ness of this space shrinks and quietens so that we become more aware of the &lt;em&gt;natural&lt;/em&gt; nature of this space. The birds, the trees, the weather are less backgrounded once the people have gone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For myself, my eyes soften – I can see without looking – and my ears relax, allowing me to hear without needing to listen. I can receive just by being, not needing to seek anything out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Which is not to say that's what I do. Clearly, I spend a huge amount of time spinning thoughts around in my head to little effect).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In other words, it becomes clearer that my long body includes strangers only after they've gone and we're in the shorter days of the year. Then the local world becomes a bit quieter and proportionately less human. The light of day is somewhat dimmed so that the sharp outlines and contrasts of spring and summer aren't so crisp. Noises are muffled by the quietness of birds and the increased hiss of the river's flow as more rain falls. Even midday walking-the-dog takes on a gloom.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;<https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content:encoded></item><item><title>Failing to teach</title><description>&lt;p&gt;For a while, the club had a strong-wristed student who had previously studied &lt;em&gt;karate&lt;/em&gt;. His posture and movement announced very clearly his deeply-grounded stability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the last times he attended, we studied 1st form &lt;em&gt;nikkyo&lt;/em&gt;, and came unstuck. From previous experience, it's moments like these that offer most learning,&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/failing-to-teach/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5c2de96a2ac40f04a4902e06</guid><category>Nikkyo</category><category>1st form</category><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 20:45:43 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content/images/2019/01/nikyo-sepia-1000.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content/images/2019/01/nikyo-sepia-1000.jpg" alt="Failing to teach"&gt;&lt;p&gt;For a while, the club had a strong-wristed student who had previously studied &lt;em&gt;karate&lt;/em&gt;. His posture and movement announced very clearly his deeply-grounded stability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the last times he attended, we studied 1st form &lt;em&gt;nikkyo&lt;/em&gt;, and came unstuck. From previous experience, it's moments like these that offer most learning, so here's my post mortem.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The challenge with studying aikido is to remember that we are not learning techniques in the way we might follow a map (turn left here, next go straight and then turn right); rather, we are creating a context within which we can study how to be and how to move with a particular feeling.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once we see the &lt;em&gt;nikkyo&lt;/em&gt; as an exercise within which certain principles are embedded, just waiting to be revealed, we can allow ourselves to become more sensitive to what's going on. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a teacher, I have something in mind when I call a student's attention to a particular detail. &lt;em&gt;Here, look at this, isn't it interesting? How might it change things?&lt;/em&gt; But if we think that a martial art is solely about fighting or self-defence, we may have the view that I should impose my superior technical skill upon him until he has to submit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This difference of perspective is precisely why I refer to the complementary roles of &lt;em&gt;nage&lt;/em&gt; (thrower) and &lt;em&gt;uke&lt;/em&gt; (receiver of the throw) as &lt;em&gt;partners&lt;/em&gt;, not opponents or attackers or enemies. When we enter a context as opponents, victory is gained by one vanquishing the other; when we work as partners, victory is victory for both (though how that looks precisely depends upon one's role).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then, add to that, the complementary roles of teacher and student, and we have a complex relationship going on. Are we attending this exercise as opponents or partners? Are we studying together, or am I teaching you? As teacher, it's my job to work with you in order to draw you to a greater level of skill. As a partner, it's my job to work with myself to develop greater resilience through sensitivity. As an opponent, it's my job to thwart you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a teacher, all too often, I want to investigate a particular detail and set the exercise up so that we can both study it comfortably. If I wanted to study that detail in a realistic context, that detail probably wouldn't emerge. In the case of &lt;em&gt;nikkyo&lt;/em&gt;, I wanted to look at how we twist around our partner's wrist rather than press on it, but for real he should already have lost his balance so that there is no opportunity to press on the wrist as it is already falling away.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To study the detail, I allowed him to stand up balanced but then his structure allowed him to resist. "This doesn't work on me," was his response.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As I write this, it seems simple and straightforward to resolve in the moment, but then it wasn't and I couldn't quite get my head around it. Days later I realised another complication:– I wasn't showing him how I do &lt;em&gt;nikkyo&lt;/em&gt; on him, I was showing him how to do &lt;em&gt;nikkyo&lt;/em&gt; on someone else, specifically a beginner.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our 1st form &lt;em&gt;nikkyo&lt;/em&gt; has at least 5 different possibilities in a single set of movements. To be clear, I don't mean different movement variations; I mean different mind movements within the physical movement. Yeah, that doesn't help much, does it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;once the &lt;em&gt;nikkyo&lt;/em&gt; wrist relationship is in place, you can extend your mind down through your fingers draping over the wrist&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;down the front of your partner&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;down through your partner's head&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;projecting through their little finger back to their head&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;projecting your fingers down and in to your own One Point&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Each way expresses more power as a result of the mind's projection, and is experienced as more powerful by the &lt;em&gt;uke&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So why, when working with a strong-wristed, stable &lt;em&gt;karateka&lt;/em&gt; was I sticking with the first way. It wasn't enough to persuade him down, so why didn't I escalate until he succumbed?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Because I'm teaching him the ladder so that he can use it with others. If I only teach him what works on him, he will not have all the options available when dealing with others. If his next &lt;em&gt;uke&lt;/em&gt; is a weak-wristed beginner, and he only has the nuclear option, he will hurt or damage them and they won't come back for more.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This isn't simply a case of being nice to others. It's also about helping them to develop stronger wrists – give them a &lt;em&gt;nikkyo&lt;/em&gt; they can handle, and they will stay with it long enough to stretch their wrists. Give them a sharp &lt;em&gt;nikkyo&lt;/em&gt;, and they will slam down without benefit to their own suppleness or strength.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When we &lt;em&gt;uke&lt;/em&gt; for someone, we are not simply offering ourselves up as cannon-fodder, patiently being thrown around until it's our turn to do the fun stuff! In fact, &lt;em&gt;ukemi&lt;/em&gt; is frequently thought of as the place where the real learning and transformation occurs. &lt;em&gt;Ukemi is the process by which the uke is opened and unlocked&lt;/em&gt; (I want to put this in quotation marks, but can't find the citation).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We walk into a dojo stiff with preconceived ideas, stiff with nerves, stiff with movement habits. Aikido (undoubtedly all the martial arts) is a transformative practice – you do not leave as the same person plus a few techniques, you have changed, you have been unlocked physically (greater suppleness and sensitivity), mentally (greater resilience and intent), and emotionally (greater freedom from emotional constraints).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That is the process of &lt;em&gt;ukemi&lt;/em&gt;, and therefore how we do &lt;em&gt;nikkyo&lt;/em&gt; matters deeply. It is not a technique that looks uniformly one way; it is a mode of relationship to another person who is putting pressure on you. It is not a device to conquer an opponent; it is a study of subtlety.&lt;/p&gt;<https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content:encoded></item><item><title>Thresholds and Liminal Spaces</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Our dojo is a temporary space:– during the day it’s a dusty village hall; in the evenings, it becomes a sacred space of learning.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Before the dojo exists, there is only &lt;em&gt;Outside&lt;/em&gt; (a community hall, profane existence, the usual). We create the &lt;em&gt;Inside&lt;/em&gt;, the dojo, by passing over the&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/thresholds-and-liminal-spaces/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5c2d60ed1afce07a4aa7bf1a</guid><category>Aikido</category><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 01:15:55 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content/images/2019/01/Takamatsu-Castle-Building-Interior-M3488.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content/images/2019/01/Takamatsu-Castle-Building-Interior-M3488.jpg" alt="Thresholds and Liminal Spaces"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our dojo is a temporary space:– during the day it’s a dusty village hall; in the evenings, it becomes a sacred space of learning.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Before the dojo exists, there is only &lt;em&gt;Outside&lt;/em&gt; (a community hall, profane existence, the usual). We create the &lt;em&gt;Inside&lt;/em&gt;, the dojo, by passing over the threshold - through liminal space. Literally, of course, each student passes through the doorway, and many schools of martial arts require that students pause to bow in the doorway, but this liminal space is larger and longer (temporally) than the doorway itself.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our liminal space is created by a process, a series of steps that serve to bring the participants from the outside, the profane world, to the inside, the sacred moment. The steps exist as rings around our central stage, each of which demands attention and negotiation before one can move on to the next:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Entering the room&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Cleaning the room&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Laying down the mats&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Putting up the signs&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Changing our clothes&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Bowing before stepping on to the mat&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Lining up in &lt;em&gt;seiza &lt;/em&gt;(kneeling), bowing&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Warming up together&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course, any one of these exists as a mundane step that just has to be done - you can’t practise in your work clothes comfortably, so you change into something appropriate for the occasion. At the same time, it also exists as a doorway through which one can catch a glimpse of another world. Of course, the Aikido kit (&lt;em&gt;kidogi&lt;/em&gt;) is a sturdy cotton material appropriate for physical activity, pulling and pushing, &lt;em&gt;AND&lt;/em&gt; it transports us to a world of martial spirit, crisp lines, cleanliness, and death. &lt;em&gt;Kidogi&lt;/em&gt; is traditional Japanese underwear, so it’s not surprising that it’s white, much like my string vest. However, white is also the traditional Japanese colour of death, so we are also garbing ourselves in funereal attire to prepare for death.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Robert Bly’s exploration of men and masculinity, &lt;em&gt;Iron John&lt;/em&gt;, the hero of the tale sets off to war on a three-legged nag, but the wild man of the woods (Iron John himself) provides him with a four-legged, nostril-flaring and -steaming, ground-thumping steed, shining and powerful. This speaks to the transformation that we experience (usually in retrospect) during our practice - we come in, limping from a day in the office, perhaps tired, perhaps a bit overwhelmed. By the end of the class, we’ve often experienced a moment of our own brilliance (or witnessed our partner’s), and return to the outside world refreshed, re-girded, and full spirited.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By returning to this ritual space week after week, year after year, we start to bring our transformed brilliance out with us when we return to the outside world. We start to walk taller, we begin to honour and speak our truths, we withstand discomfort without collapsing or pushing it away. We begin to live from our Inside - the Inside of the dojo has created a space for and awareness of our inner warrior. We find that we have a guide within us who seeks to help us navigate through the Outside.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And the death? Every time we fall over, every time we fail, we have an opportunity to die a little on the mat. And every single small death is a shedding of an old skin, bringing a new, lithe skin to the surface. Every small death invites us to let go of the old knowledge and experience, and to open up to new possibilities. This, then, is a death to be sought out and celebrated!&lt;/p&gt;<https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content:encoded></item><item><title>Extend your mind</title><description>&lt;p&gt;A simple phrase that contains universes! The two meanings that I am working on are &lt;em&gt;intention&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;awareness&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Intention here does not mean "I'm going to ... at some point in the future". It means using the mind to create direction, e.g. if I point to you, a direction is&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/principle-4-extend-your-mind/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5c2b8c32b44f424bb6abe260</guid><category>principles</category><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 16:00:38 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content/images/2019/01/kyudo.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content/images/2019/01/kyudo.jpg" alt="Extend your mind"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A simple phrase that contains universes! The two meanings that I am working on are &lt;em&gt;intention&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;awareness&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Intention here does not mean "I'm going to ... at some point in the future". It means using the mind to create direction, e.g. if I point to you, a direction is created from me to you that travels down along my arm, hand, finger, and continues through the air to you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the same time, when we extend our mind, we increase our awareness, so that our nervous system is retrieving more information.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is both being and doing, receptive and active, awareness and intention.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regular practice has a subtle effect on the body – which for the first months of training may not show up at all – but over time contributes to a clear feeling (i.e. sensations of wholeness, of direction) through the body.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I first started training, when told to extend my mind I would think strongly in a direction, without any internal feedback from my body. Then someone would test my structure, and I'd see that I had gained stability. After a period of this, when we went to the pub at the end of the class, I was aware of a certain feeling of aliveness (beyond that of simply having been moving for 2 hours). It felt good. After a further period, I started to notice that feeling lingering when I woke up the following morning. And so the feeling became a more frequent and longer-staying guest, until it became quietly resident in my system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As to what actually happens when we extend our mind – I'm not sure, but reading &lt;em&gt;&lt;em&gt;Born To Walk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/em&gt; recently may have given me a clue. When walking, as we bring our weight on to one leg to free up the other, the fascia in that leg gets stretched, and at a certain point of stretch, the fascia sends signals to the local muscles to prompt them to contract slightly (isometrically). This combination of fascial tissue stretch and slight muscular contraction stiffens the leg, thus stabilising it to bear our weight.&lt;/p&gt;<https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content:encoded></item><item><title>Have a Light Posture</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Stand tall, allow uplift, experience the ground pushing your skeleton upwards.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/principle-3-have-a-light-posture/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5c2b8bebb44f424bb6abe25a</guid><category>principles</category><dc:creator>James Knight</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 15:49:44 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content/images/2019/01/hudson-hintze-268381-unsplash.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content/images/2019/01/hudson-hintze-268381-unsplash.jpg" alt="Have a Light Posture"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stand tall, allow uplift, experience the ground pushing your skeleton upwards.&lt;/p&gt;<https://hoardinghopes.github.io/falling-uphill/content:encoded></item></channel></rss>